<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Here beginneht [sic] a merye iest of a man that was called Howleglas, and of many marueylous thinges and iestes that he dyd in his lyfe, in Eastlande and in many other places</title>
            <title>Till Eulenspiegel. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00434</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853086</idno>
  <idno type="VID">18452</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248561611</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 10564</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S117877</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99853086e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00434)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18452)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 39:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Here beginneht [sic] a merye iest of a man that was called Howleglas, and of many marueylous thinges and iestes that he dyd in his lyfe, in Eastlande and in many other places</title>
                  <title>Till Eulenspiegel. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Tamestrete at the Vintre on the thre Craned wharfe by Wyllyam Copland],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1560?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon. Suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Thirty-two lines to the page. C2 recto line 1 has: sayd .. with--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; cropped and torn affecting print; lacks quire D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18452:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18452:1"/>
            <p>Here beginneht a me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye Iest of a man that was called Howleglas, and of many marueylous thinges and Iestes that he dyd in his lyfe, in Eastlande and in many other places.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of two men (one with pitchfork and bare head, one hooded) standing before a seated monarch</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18452:2"/>
            <p>FOr the great desyryng and praying of my good frandes. And I y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> first writer of this boke might not denye thē. Thus haue I compled &amp; gathered much knauyshnes &amp; falsnes of one Howleglas made and done within his lyfe, whiche Howleglas dyed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yeare of our lorde God. M.CCCC. &amp; .L. Nowe I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre to be pardoned both before ghostly &amp; worldly, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore highe &amp; lowe afore noble and vnnoble. And right lowly I requyre all those y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> shall reade or heare this presēte Ieste (my ignoraūce to excuse.) This fable is not but only to renewe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mindes of men or women, of all degrees frō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vse of sadnesse to passe the tyme, with laughter or myrthe, And for because y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple knowyng persones shuld beware if folkes can see. Me thinke it is better no passe the tyme with suche a mery Ieste and laughe there at and doo no synne: than for to wepe and do synne,</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <head>¶ Howe Howleglas as he was borne, was christened thre tymes vpon one daye.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:18452:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>N the lande of Sassen, in the vyllage of Ruelnige, there dwelleth a mā that was named Hicholas Nowleglas that had a wife named Wypeke, that lay a childbed in the same wyllage: and that chylde was borne to christening &amp; named Tyell Howleglas. And than the chyld was brought into a tauerne where y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> father was wyth his gosseppes and made good chere whan the mydwife had wel dronke, she toke y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> childe to bere it home, and in the wai was a litle bridg ouer a muddy water. And as the mydwife would haue gōe ouer the lytle brydge, she fel into the mudde with the chylde, for she had a lytel dronk to much wyne, for had not helpe come quickly the had both be drowned in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mudde. And whā the came home with the childe, the made a kettle of warm water to be made redi &amp; therf they washed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> child clen of the mudde. And this was Howleglas thre tymes in one dai cristened Once at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> churche, once in the mudde, &amp; once in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> warm water</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe that Howleglas whan that he was a chylde, aunswered a man that asked the waye.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon a tīe went Howleglas father &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther out &amp; left Howleglas withī y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> house Than cāe ther a man rydyng half into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dore &amp; asked is there nobody within? thā answered y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chyld yes ther is a man &amp; a halfe, &amp; a horse head. Than asked the mā wher is thy father? And the child āswerid &amp; sayd, my father is of yl, makīg worse: And my mother is gōe for scath or shame And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> man
<pb facs="tcp:18452:3"/> sayd to the childe, how vnderstandest thou that? &amp; thā the chylde sayd: My father is makyng of yl worse, for he ploweth the felde and maketh great holes that mē should fall therin whan the ride And my mother is to borow bread, and whan she geueth it agayne and gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uete lesse it is shame, and whā she geueth it &amp; geueth more that is scathe. Than said the man which is the way to ryde? and the chyld aunswered and sayd there where the gees go, and than rode y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> man his way to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gees and when he came to the gees the flew into the water, than wist he not wher to ryd but turned again to the chyld and sayd the gees be flowē into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> water, and thus wot I not what to doo nor whether to ryde Than aunswered the childe ye must ryde where as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gees go, and not where the swyme. Than departed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> man and rode hys way &amp; marueyled of the answer of the childe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas sat vpō hys fathers hors behind hym.</head>
               <p>MAny greate cōplayntes cāe before the father of Howleglas, how his sone was a deceuer of folkes, and a great mocker. This complaint was made on hym whan he could go, and whan he lay in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cradle, he tumbled vpon the quisshins wyth hys arse vpward, and whan he came to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> age of nyne yere old: he let no vngraciousnes scape fro hym, in so muche y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all the neybours complayned on hym. Than sayd his father to him howe commeth this that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>playneth soo to mee, they say that ye be a mocker &amp; a deceyuer? Than sayde Howleglas good father I doo nobody harme and that shall I shew vnto you. Take
<pb facs="tcp:18452:3"/> a horse and go vpon his backe and I wyll ryde behind you than you shal see what the people wyll say to me and than lyght his father vpon his horse and toke his soone behynde hym, and whan he was vpon the horse he shewed the peple his arse. Thā said the folke what vngracious knaue and begyler is that? Than sayde Howleglas to his father nowe may ye heare, I holde my peace and speake neuer a woorde, and yet saye the that I am a knaue and a deceyuer of folke. And than his father toke him and sette hym before hym on the horse, and thā began he to grin &amp; put out his tongue vpon the people that his father sawe not, &amp; than the people sayde see what a cursed young knaue is there. Than sayd his father to Howleglas, thou was borne in an vnhappy tyme, for now thou sittest before me &amp; doest no body harme: &amp; yet for al that they do call the a knaue and a begiler. And so departed Houleglas fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the land of Mayd a brochim a village frō thence where his wyfe was, &amp; within short space dyed And than abid Howleglas mother with him, and eat and dranke together suche as the might gette, for she was but pore, &amp; Howleglas would go to no craft but when he was sixtene yeare old he began to daūce vpō a corde, and no otherwyse.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas fell fro the rope into the water wherof the people had good sporte.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">V</seg>Pon a tyme Howleglas played vpō y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> corde that was set ouer the water, wher he made good sport, but at the last there was one y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> cut the rope, so fell he into the water &amp; wās all to wette, &amp; he came out as well as he might, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lytle
<pb facs="tcp:18452:4"/> spyte he thought to quyte thē a gayn. And said to thē come agayne to morowe and I wyll doo many more wōdres vpō the rope. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> next dai after came How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas and daunced vpon the corde, and than he sayde to the yonge folke ye shall see what newes I can doo. Gyue me euery body your ryghte shoe vpon the rope ende so they dyd, and the olde men also. And whan he hadde daunced a whyle he caste them their shone vpō a hepe and bad them take their shoen eche of them a gayne. Than ran they after their shoene and for haste one tumbled ouer the other, and than the began to ly together by the eares, and smyte with their fystes soo hard that the fell both to the yearth. One said wepīg this is my sho, and the other laughed and cryd that is my shoe. And thus for their shoene laye they together by the eares. Than began Howleglas to laughe, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing seeke your shoene: eesterday ye bathed me, and he lept fro the corde and went his way to his mothers, &amp; durst not come out agaī ī the space of a moneth. And so he taried with his mother, wherof his mother was glad but she knew not the cause why he dyd with her, nor what he had done.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howlglas mother learned hym and bad hym go to a crafte.</head>
               <p>Wybeke the mother of Howleglas was glad that her sonne Howleglas was so sottele and wyse, &amp; she sayd that he myght not lyue so and get moni as therwith. And than she sayde to her sonne that he should learne a craft. And than answered Howleglas to his mother, what thing it that that a body should dyspose himself to, that should abid by him al his life
<pb facs="tcp:18452:4"/> And his mother aunswered clene contrary &amp; sayde y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> me also thīketh for in .iii. daies I haue had no bread ī my house should I not abid &amp; suffre al my lyfe? I had leuer die. Than said Howleglas this is not an āswer to my question, but I will aunswer now to yours, &amp; said. A poore man y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hath nothing to eate he must fast saint Nycholas day, and he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hath meate may eat on saint Martins euen. And in likewyse it is with you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas gat bread for. his mother.</head>
               <p>AS Howleglas mother was thus w<seg rend="sup">t</seg>out bred thā be thought howleglas how he might best get bread for her. Than went he out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> village to a towne thereby called stafforde, &amp; went into a bakers house, where he asked y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> baker if he wold send his lord for .iii.s. bread. som whit and some rye, &amp; he named a lorde that was of an other land, but he at that tyme was lodged at an Inne in the towne, &amp; bad the baker let one go with him &amp; that he should haue his money &amp; the baker was content. And than Howleglas gaue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> baker a bagge that had a hole in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> botom, &amp; therin put he the bread &amp; so departed with the bakers ladd &amp; whan he was in an other streat he let fal .iii. whyte loues at the hole in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> durt. And than bad howleglas to the bakers seruaunt sete downe the bagge &amp; goo fetch me other whyte breade for this, for I dare not bere it to my lord. And than went y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bakers seruaūt home to chaunge the bread, and in the meane whyle went Howleglas w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the sacke of bread home to hys mothers. And whan the bakers seruaūt came again to the place and found not Howleglas, he retourned home againe &amp; told his master how Howleglas hade
<pb facs="tcp:18452:5"/> serued him. A than the baker heard that Howleglas was gon his way with his bread: than ran y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> baker to the Inne that Howleglas named him, &amp; asked the ser<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uātes of the lordes for Howleglas, but the said ther came none suche, &amp; than knew the baker that he was deceyued &amp; so returned home. Than said Howleglas to his mother, eate and make mery now you haue it &amp; whan you haue nomore ye must faste.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas creeped into a bae hyue, &amp; howe he was stolen in the nyght</head>
               <p>VPō a tyme went Howleglas w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his mother to the didecagiō of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> churche. And there he drāke so muche that he was dronkē, &amp; than wente he into a garden therby, where stode many bee hiues &amp; ther he sought wher he might haue a place to slepe in, &amp; at the laste he founde an emptye bee hyue, wherin he put hym self to slepe for that nyght. Than came therin the ded of the nyghte, two theues for to steale a way the hyues, and they felte which of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues was heuiest, for they thought therin was moost hony, so at the last they felt the heuy that Howleglas was in and than sayd the thefe too his felowe here is on that is very heuy this will I haue, take thou ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; let vs go. Than toke thei the bee hiues on ther neckes &amp; departed. Than awoke Howleglas &amp; herd al what the said, And it was so darke that the one knew not the other Than put Howleglas his hāde out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hyue, and pulled the foremost by the heare where with he was angry and saede to his lelowe behynde hym, Why pullest y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> me by the here? And than he answered.
<pb facs="tcp:18452:5"/> I pull the by the here &amp; I haue as muche as I can do to bere my hyue, And within a whyle after he pulled the hyndermoste by the here that was ryghte angrye and sayde, I bere so heui that I swete, and for al that thou pullest me by the hery? Thou andswered the for moste thou lyest, how should I plucke the by the here and I can scantly fynde my waye, and thus went the chydyng by the way and as they were chiding: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leglas put out his hand againe &amp; puled the foremoste by the here, wherof he was angry and set downe hys hyue and toke his felowe by the head, &amp; thus they tū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled together by the here in the strete and at the laste whan the one had well beten the other, the ran their waye and lefte the hyues lying. and than slepte How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas in the be hyue til in the mornyng, and than he arose and went forthe, and as he wente he came by a castell and went in, and the lorde asked him if he wold haue a maister and he said yes, and than the lord hired hym and vpon a tyme he rode with his maister bi the way wher stode hempe. Than said his maister to him whan thou fyndest suche seede shyte therin, for there with men be hanged vpon the gallowes, and vpō the wheeles, both theues and morderers. Than āswered Howleglas that he wold do it and his maister said so because that he was a thefe, and in the night went a robbyng and a steling for he lyued almost therby. On a tyme as his maister was at supper the cooke called Howleglas and badde hym go into the seller &amp; fetche him the mustarde out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pot. And than went How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leglas &amp; he vnderstode that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cooke bad him go fetch a hempen rope. Than marueyled he what he mēt for he neuer sawe none afore. Than thought he, wyll he
<pb facs="tcp:18452:6"/> binde me therwith, than went Howleglas into the se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler, and there he sought about, and at the last he foūd the pot, with mustard, and than he remembred hym &amp; sayd, my maester bad me that where I foūd any such sede that I shold shite therin, and than he put his arse ouer the pot, and shyt therin a great heape, and than he styrred it about together and brought it to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> coke and thā he cooke dressed the mustarde in saucers and send them to the table and the lorde tasted, and it sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored il thā said he to the cooke what haue you groūd in the mustarde, for it sauerethe lyke as there were a turde therin? And than began Howleglas to laughe, than said his maister wherat laughest thou? thynkeste thou we con not taste? than taste thou. And than aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered Howleglas I eate no mustarde, for wote you not what ye bad me do whan that werode ouer suche sede, that whā I foūd such sede you that than I should shyte in it for with such sede you sayd men were han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: and so haue I shytten in the seede. Than saide his maister, a thou vnhappy knaue this seede is not lyke the sede of hemp: but I knowe this by very good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son that thou hast dōe it of cursednes &amp; great falsnes, and than he toke a staffe and wold haue smyted How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leglas. And than Howleglas tooke his legges and ran away, &amp; his maister after him, but he coulde not ouer take him. Than he returned home agayn and Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas would no more come there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas was hered of a priest.</head>
               <p>AS Howleglas ran out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> castel, he cam to a village that was called Buddest ī the land of Brounswike. And ther came a priest to Howleglas and hyred hym, but he knew him not: &amp; the priest sayd
<pb facs="tcp:18452:6"/> to hym that he shoulde haue good dayes and eate ād drynke the same meate that he himselfe &amp; his woman dyd. and al that should be done with halfe the labour &amp; than sayd Howleglas y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> there after would he do his diligēce. Then dressed the priestes woman to chikins and she bad Howleglas turne and so he dyd, and he lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked vp and sawe that she had but one iye, that whan the chikins were enough: thā he brake one of the chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyns fro the spyt, and eate it with out any bread, ād when it was dener tyme, came the woman into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chin where Howleglas turned, &amp; thought to take vp the chikyns: and whan she was come, she founde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more there but one chikyn. Than sayde she to Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas, where is the other chikyn? there were two chyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kins than answered he to her, lift vp your iye: &amp; than shal you se the other chiken, than was the womā ther with angry &amp; knew well that Howleglas mocked her and than she ran to the priest &amp; told him howe she had dressed .ii. chykins, &amp; whā she came to take thē vp shee foūd but one, &amp; thā he mocked me because I had but one iye: than went the priest to Howleglas, &amp; said whi mocke ye my woman: there was .ii. chikyns? than an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swerd Howleglas &amp; said that was truth, I haue said to the woman that she should open her eyen, and shee should se well where that other chekyn was become. Than laughed the priest &amp; sayd she cannot se she hath but one iye: than sayd Howleglas to the priest, the on chykin haue I eaten, for ye sayd that I shold eate and drinke as well as you and your woman, and the one I eate for you, and the other I eate for your woman for I was afrayde that you shoulde haue synned, for the promise that ye promysed me, &amp; therfore I made
<pb facs="tcp:18452:7"/> mesure Thā sayd the priest I care not for the chikēs but I wold haue you please my woman and do after her. Then sayd Howleglas I do your cōmaūdement and that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> womā bad him do, he did but halfe for she bad him fetch a boket of water, &amp; he went &amp; brought it but halfe full of water, &amp; whā he shold brynge two loogges he brought but one, &amp; when he should geue the beastes two botels of hay, he haue thē but one, &amp; whan he should fetch a pot ful of bere, he brought it halfe full, &amp; so did he of many other thinges mo. Thā complayned she to the prest of Howleglas again thā sayd y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> priest. I bad that you shold do as she bad you and Howleglas answered I haue done as ye had me for ye said to me y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I shold do al thing w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> halfe labour And your woman would fayne see w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> both iyes: but she seeth but with one iye and so do I halfe y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> labour &amp; than the priest laughed: and than said y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wōan, wyl you haue this vngracious knaue am lenger: thā wil not I tary no leuger w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you but depart. Than gaue the priest Howleglas leue to depart for his womans sake, but whan the paryshe clerke was dead of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> vil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lage, thā sent the priest for Howleglas, &amp; holye hyme so muche that that he was made the paryshe clerke</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas was made clerke of Buddenestde,</head>
               <p>AS Howleglas was clarke of the Churche, he shuld helpe the priest to sing masse, and as he stode afore the alter with the preest, the preest lette a great fart that al the churche range therof. Thā said Howleglas syr person what offer you there, our lord for frankinsence? Than answered the person, what haste thou to do there wyth? for I haue the power to
<pb facs="tcp:18452:7"/> shite in the middes of the churche, and I wyll. Than said Howleglas I hold a barel of beare that you shal not shyte in the myddle therof. Than sayd the pryest I holde you, thynke you that I am not so hardy nor bolde to doo that? Than tourned the parson hym a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout and went and shite in the church a great heape and sayd clarke I haue wonne the barell of bere, thā siyd Howleglas y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ye haue not, for we wyl first meete whether it be in the middes of the church or not And than they met it, and it lacked of the mydle more thā vi. fote, and than wan Howleglas the barell of bere, werof the priestes leman was angry, &amp; sayd you wyll kepe this vngracious knaue so longe w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> at the last he wyll shame you. And than in the meane season while Howleglas was paryshe clarke, at Easter they should play the resurrectiō of our lord, &amp; for because than the mene wer not learned nor could not read, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> priest toke his leman and put her in the graue for an aungell, and this seing Howleglas toke to hym, ii. of the symplest persons y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> were in the towne that plaied the .iii. maries, and the parson plaied Christe, with a baner in his hand, than saide Howleglas to the sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple persons, whā the aungel asketh you whome you seke. you may saye the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eman with one iye. Than it fortuned that the tyme was come that thei must playe &amp; the angell asked them whō they sought &amp; than said they as Howleglas had shewed &amp; lerned them afore. &amp; than answered they, we seke the priests leman with one iye: and than the priest myght heare that he was mocked. And whan the priestes leman herd that, she arose out of the graue and would haue smyten with her fist Howleglas vpon the cheke. but
<pb facs="tcp:18452:8"/> she missed him &amp; smote one of the simple parsons that played one of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thre maries, &amp; he gaue her another, &amp; than toke she him by the heare, &amp; that seing his wyfe: came running hastely to smite the priest leaman, and than the priest seing this: caste downe hys baner, and went to helpe his woman, so that the one gaue the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther sore strokes and made great noyse in the churche And than Howleglas seyng them lyinge to gether by the eares in the bodi of the church, went his way out of the village and came no more there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe that Howleglas would flee fro the towne house of Meybrough.</head>
               <p>AFter that cāe Howleglas to Maybrough wher he dyd many marueyleous thynges y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> his name was there wel knowen. Than bad the principal of the towne, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he should do some thing y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was neuer sene before: Than sayd he that he woulde go to the hi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ghest of the counsail house, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ye fro it, and anon that was knowen through all the towne that Howleglas woul flye fro the tope of the councel house, in sōuche that all the towne was ther assembled &amp; gathered in the market place to see him. Vpō the top of the house stod howleglas with his hands wauering as though he would haue flyen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an the people loked whan he should haue flyed: wherat he laughed, and sayde to the people: I thought there had bene no more fooles but my self? but I se wel y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> her is a hole town ful. For had ye altogether said y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ye wold haue fliē: yet I wold not haue beleued you. And now ye beleue one fore y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> sayth that he will flye which thing is vnpossible for I haue no winges, &amp; no mā can flie without wynges. And than went he his waye fro the top of the coūsail
<pb facs="tcp:18452:8"/> house &amp; lefte the folke there standing. And than depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> folke fro thēce som blamīg him &amp; som laughing sayīg he is a shrewed fole for he telleth vs the truthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas made him selfe a phecision. and how he begyled a doctour of the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shopps of Mayborough.</head>
               <p>THe byshope Eryme of Mayborough, Earle of Quecforthe &amp; all his nobles loued Howleglas, for that he did many propre conceites, and therfore the Bys<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoppe gaue him meate and drynke, clothe, and wages. The bysshop had a ryghte wyse doctoure withe hym and he in no wyse myght here norse no fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les. So vpon a tyme as he sawe Howleglas there, he sayd to the byshoppe and the lordes men, you shoulde lette come in lordes Courtes wyse men, and no foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les: for the wyse men, will be conuersaunt with wyse men and geue wyse reasons. And fooles will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersaunt with fooles, and geue folish reasons. And than aunswered they and sayde that reason is false, for he that folishnes wyll not here nor see, he maye well depart from them. There bee also that thynke themself wise y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> bene often temes defiled of fooles, it belonges to prynces, lordes, and barrons, to haue in their courtes fooles: for oftentymes they driue a wai heuy thoughtes and fantasies and melancoly. Where lordes be, there will be also fooles. Than sayd Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas to the lordes, what argumēt haue you had withe the doctour for my sake? forsoth he shalbe quit &amp; you will helpe me therto: and they sayde all yes. Than de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted he out of the court by the space of .iii. wekes, and than came a gayne to Genckestayne, and than he came to the lodging there where the doctour laye and
<pb facs="tcp:18452:9"/> was sicke for the whiche likenes he sought for helpe: Than sayd the lordes, that there was come a rūnīge man and a maister of Phisecke that had helped mani people. The doctour knewe not Howleglas. and than he tooke hym by the arme and ledde hym into his lod<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyng where he spake to hym &amp; sayde, and ye can helpe me, I shall contente you well for your labour: Than aunswred he I trust to helpe you, but first I must lye by you one nyght, that I may couer you wel that you may swete, and by the ayre of the swete, I shall well knowe what syckenes it is that you haue. And thā y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> priest wenyng that al had bene true: graunted to him and than gaue Howleglas to him a strong purgacion for to make him shyte, but he said to the doctour y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it was a medicī to meke him to sweat, and the doctour beleued hym. And than went Howeleglas into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and there stode a pot, the which Howleglas toke and shit in, and he tooke the pot &amp; put it betwene the bed and the wal of the doctour, that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> doctour knew it not, and the doctour went a fore to bed, &amp; thā came Howleglas to bede, and the priest turned him to the wall where the pot stode, and then he felt such a stinke of the durt that stode in the pot, so that he tourned his head a gayn toward Hawleglas, than let Howleglas a great stynking fart, and than tourned the doctoure a gain toward the wall. and than stanke the durte in the pot, &amp; thus suffred the doctour the stynke half the night that him thought his heart did break and than began the medicine to worke so much that he be shyt al the bed, thā said Rowlegias how do ye maister doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour? me thinke your swete stinkethe very sore y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure thoughte in his mynde that knowe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> I well
<pb facs="tcp:18452:9"/> enough but he myght not speke because of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> stinke. Than said Howleglas I wil go fetch you a candell, &amp; se how it is with you, and as he rose he let a gret fart Than sayd the doctour, alas I dye. But he thanked God that Howleglas was gone: that he myght haue some ayre. Than began the daye to appeare, &amp; soo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted Howleglas his way. And than loked the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour by the beddes syde: and ther founde the pot of durt that stanke so, and than tooke he it and cast it a wai, and than knew he wel that he was mocked. And within a whyle came the byshop &amp; his nobles to viset the doctour, and whan the came to his chamber, the asked hym howe he fared and he aunswered and sayd neuer worse. For I am all moste dead. Than he tolde the beshop how y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> maister of phisicke had serued hym and than begā the byshop to laugh and all his lordes And sayd this cometh to passe all after your wordes. For ye sayd that fooles wold haue couersacion with fooles: and geue folysh reasons, and wise men would haue cōuersaciō with wyse mē: &amp; geue wyse reasons. But I se that mani wyse: be made fooles of fooles, &amp; so be you: For if that ye wold haue suffred howleglas and sayd nothyng: ye had not be mocked of hym. For the phisiciō that was with you was Howleglas, and that we all knewe well enoughe. But in no wyse we wold shew you: for because ye were so wise y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he shold be begyled of a foole. For ther is no mā that is wyse, but he must know fooles, for wher no fooles be, how should men know wyse folke? And than the doctour held his peace and spake no more, and than neuer af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter durst he complaī more of fooles, but let them do all that they would after theyr owne mynde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18452:10"/>
               <head>How Howleglas made a sicke childe shite that a fore myght not shyte, and howe he gat great wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyp therof and prayse.</head>
               <p>MEn let alone, and take no hede of cunning mē y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> dwel bi thē: but profer thē a litle or nought for ther labour, nor be beloued: but rurall persones, &amp; vacabūdes haue all their desyre. As it is don to How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas, that came into the lande of Hyldeshe, in a lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging wher the good man was not at home, but How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>legias was welcom to the good wife of the house. In the house there was a sicke chylde lying by the fyre. And than Howleglas seing the chyld lye so: he asked his hostise, what sicknes that the chyld had? Than an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swered the woman to Howleglas &amp; sayde, if the chyld might go to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> draught: he shold do well ynough. And than aunswered Howleglas therto, know you no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy than aunswered the Woman? Can ye helpe the chylde? &amp; ye can: I shall geue you that ye shall be plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sed therwith. Thā answered Howleglas, that is but a lytle thing to do, nor no cunning. For I wil take no thyng therfore. And so departed the wife into the gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den, and in the meane whyle: dyd Howleglas shyte a grean turde, &amp; than set he the shyting chayre ouer the turde, and set the chylde theron, as though y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chylde had done it. Than came the woman out of the gardē &amp; asked wo had done that. And thā answered Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas I haue done it. ye sayd that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> chyld could not go to the draught, therfore I haue set the chylde in the chayre. Than toke the woman the chylde awaye, and sawe so much durt vnderneth. Than said she to How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas, this is it that hath hindered the chyld so long for this great cure ye must haue great thanke therof
<pb facs="tcp:18452:10"/> Than sayd Howleglas suche maistery can I do with lesse cost. Than sayde the woman I praye you larne me that cunnyng and I will geue you thear for what you wyll haue. Than sayd Howleglas. I muste nedes depart from hence, but whan I come a gayne I wyll learne you that science and learnyng and then wente he into the stable and sadled his horse and toke his le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue and so departed from thence. But he tought not his hostes that science: but so departed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas made hole al the sicke folke, that were in the Hospitall, where the spere of our lorde is</head>
               <p>VPon a tyme Howleglas came to Northebo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rough, and he set vpon the churche dores, &amp; vpō. y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Guyld hal, &amp; euery place y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in that towne myght knowe that he was a great maister of Phisicke: That al sicke he could make hol And than the maister of the spytle house, where the sper of our lord is: had mani sicke folkes in his house than went the maister of the hospytall to Howleglās &amp; asked hym, yf he could helpe sicke men, or lame mē and make them hole? &amp; he woulde reward him after his owne pleasure. Thā answered howleglas to the maister of the hospital, wyl ye geue me .cc. golde gyle dens, and I shal recouer and make thē hole of all the sicknes, &amp; deases, and will haue no money tyll all the sicke persons be deliuered out of the hospital. These wordes pleased the maister of the hospitall veri wel. And he gaue hym some money in his hande. Vpon. y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> morowe after came howleglas to the hospital w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> .ii. men after hym, &amp; than he asked y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sicke folke, on after the other, what desease they had, anb whan he hadde asked them all than he made thē swere vpon a booke
<pb facs="tcp:18452:11"/> that thei should kepe his counsail whatsoeuer he said to them. They answered that they would, than saide Howleglas to them, I haue vndertaken to make you all hole whiche is vnpossible, but I must nedes bren one of you all to pouder. And than must I take they pouder of him: &amp; geue all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other to drinke therof, w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> other medicines that i shall minister therto And he y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is the last, whā I shal cal you out of the hospitall, and he that can not go: shalbe he that shalbe brēned. For on wednesday next cōming. than shall I come before the maister of the hospitall, and than shall I call and he that slepeth longest shall pay for al than prepared euery one of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> sicke folke their crutches, &amp; gere y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thy wold eot be the laste. And whā Howleglas was come to the maisters of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hospitall: thā called he thē, &amp; than they ran out of the hospitall, &amp; some of them had not bene out of their bed in .x. yere before. than whan the sicke folke were out of the hospital. than asked he his mony, &amp; than the maister gaue it him &amp; than he depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted. And within .iii. daies after came again the poore men to they hospital: &amp; complained of ther sicknes, &amp; than the maister of the hospital said to them, how cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this to passe? I gaue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> maister of phisik a great sūme of mony to make you hole. than answered the poore folke, he hathe deceyued you and vs bothe, for four dayes past he came to euery one of vs, and sayd to vs that he should come on wednisday next coming and heale vs, but he sayd he must nedes first bren on of vs, and sayd that should be he that whan he shold cal, shold be the last out of hys bed, and the pouder of hym shold they drinke &amp; be made hole therwith. than knewe the maister of the hospitall that he was decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:18452:11"/> and begyled, and than toke he the poore folke īto the hospitall and put euery one in their bedde as the were before but he dyd all a gaynst his wyll.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How that a baker hyred Howleglas to be his seruaunt.</head>
               <p>VPon a time came Howleglas to a baker for to dwell, and the baker had ned of a seruāt and than he hyred Howleglas. In the next mornynge after, must the baker bake: so the nyght before must Howleglas syft thei meale without a candell. Than said he to his maister, ye must geue me a candel. Thā aūswered y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> baker I neuer gaue a candel to boult w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> but the did boult in the mone light. Than aūswered Howleglas I am contente, than went his maister to bed to slepe .iii. houres, and in the mean whyle, let he the bulting bag out of the window in the mone shine and than began he to boult the flowre vpon the erth ī the garden. Than arose his maister and thought to haue baken: and came to the boulting house, and thā he sawe that Howleglas, had boulted y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> meale in thei garden vpon the bare grounde. Than sayd the baker to Howleglas, what the deuyll doest thou thinke, the mele cost no more but strawing vpon the earth? than aunswered Bowleglas to his maister. I haue doone as ye bad me: for it is boulted in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mone shyne. Than aūswered the baker. I badde the that thou shouldest boulte it by the mooue shyne: &amp; than answered How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leglas, so I haue done, for it is syfted in the mone shy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, and without the mone shyne. And than sayd how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas. There is not much mele lost, but that we mai take it vp a gayne. And thā answered the baker it is to late nowe for to bake, for our dowe is not made.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18452:12"/>
               <p>Than answered Howleglas to his maister &amp; sayde, I shall helpe you wel. your neighboure hath dowe redy made in the kneding trough, &amp; I wyll go fetch that: &amp; put yours ī y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> stede. Thā was the baker much angry and bad hem to the galowes &amp; fetche y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was vnder it, and than said Howleglas he woulde, &amp; than he depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to the galowes, &amp; whan he came there: he foūd no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thīg els but a few bones &amp; those he toke vp &amp; brought home with hym. And than said to his maister, I haue brought that that I haue found vnder the galowes what wil ye do wite it? Thā was the baker more an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry &amp; sayd. I shall cōplayne on the, thou haste stolen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the kynges iustice. than wente oute to the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket &amp; Howleglas folowed &amp; than came y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> baker to the burges of the town, &amp; began to complaine. And than came Howleglas &amp; stode by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> baker, &amp; therwith was thei baker so angry that he wiste not what to saye to the burges and said āgerly to Howleglas, what wilt thou haue? than sayd Howleglas I must nedes se the complaynt that ye make on me. than answered y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker, go out of mi sight thou vngracious knaue, than aunswred Howleglas to they baker, if I were in thy iyes, thā must I nedes passe through thy nose thrills whan y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> shyttest thi iyes. than departed the burges. &amp; knewe wel that he mocked. And than shewed Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas his arse to the baker, and asked hym if he coulde bake suche a lofe in his mouth. A than departed he &amp; left the baker standyng in the market place.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How howleglas was put in wages with the foster of anhalte, for to watche vpon a toure, to se whan his enemies came: and than for to blowe an horne to warne them therof.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18452:12"/>
               <p>APon a time y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> erle of Anholte hired for a true wayther Holeglas, for he had many enemies &amp; for that couse he must haue many souldiers in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that he must geue meate to. But Howleglas y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was ī the toppe of the toure, was not of the meriest, for the was forget. Wpon a tyme cam his enemies, &amp; fetched a waye a great flocke af the earles beastes, &amp; that sawe Howleglas. but he helde his peace: &amp; that was spyed and shewed to the earle. And thā the erle asked hym, why he dyd lye so styll &amp; blew not. Than aunswered Hdwleglas, I dyd daunce for my meate. Thā sayd the earle. wil ye not blowe enemies. Than aunswered Howleglas I dare not, the fielde is so ful of enemies. For if I should blowe: they wold come &amp; slee you at youre owne gate. And thā the earle was cōtēt &amp; departed And within a while after was How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas agayne forgottē, And whan the earle was at dyner and had gread daītes before him: Howleglas blewe ēemies. And by &amp; by the erle &amp; al his souldiers rose fro the table &amp; dressed thē in harnes &amp; ran to the gate, but they foūde no enemies, In the meane why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le toke howleglas as much meate as he would haue fro the earles table. Thā the souldiers and the earle came in &amp; called Howleglas to them, &amp; the erle asked hym why he blewe enemies &amp; there were none. the erle sayd it was a trayterous dede, &amp; thā he put him out of office. Thā must he nedes run with his foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mē to syghte with their enemies, than saide he that for thinketh me. I wold I wer hēce but he could not Vpā a time came enemies thā wēt the souldiers out vpon them, and Howleglas was last: and whan they retourned agayne he was the fyrste in at the gate,
<pb facs="tcp:18452:13"/> at the last the erle had knowlege and came to Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas, and asked what was the cause that he was the last out, and the first in? Than answered Howleglas to the erle. worshypfull lord if it plese you, whā your souldiours made good there: I stode vpon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tour fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting and therfore I am not so strong as your souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be, and that is cause that I am last oute: and the fyrst in. And you wil geue me meate ynough as ye do y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other, than shall I be the first. Than answered the erle, thynkest thou that I wyll kepe the so longe as I haue kept y<seg rend="sup">e</seg>, to do nothyng but mocke vs in this ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner, as ye haue done so often? Than gaue he Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas leue to departe, wherof he was very glad, for he loued no fyghtyng: and so departed he.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas whan the kinges foole of Casme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Poseyn withe a great point of folishnes.</head>
               <p>THe kyng of Casmer he had with him a certayn foole, whiche foole could playe vpon the fedle, wherfore the kyng loued hym much &amp; set great price by hym. Also the kyng harde oftentymes tell of How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas: but he neuer could se hī. And on a time it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuned that howleglas came in to the kynges palaice for to aske dwelling, wherof when that the kyng wist that Howleglas was come there to dwell: he was ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry glad therof, and toke him in, and made hym goodly there. So it fortuned that the kīges foole and How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leglas could not agree, and that spyed the kyng well, and thought in his mynde what shal I doo? and than he made thē both to be brought before him in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hall and than he sayde to them. Whiche of you two can y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> moste foolyshnes? And one of you doo that the other wyll not do: I shall geue hym newe clothyng, and .xx. ducates
<pb facs="tcp:18452:13"/>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="8 pages">
                     <desc>〈8 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18452:14"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18452:14"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he had done to them: for y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he was welcome to no place that he came to wher he had be much made of before all in his youth, Than bethought Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas in what maner he might get mony with litle la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boure. Than wente Howleglas &amp; got him a priestes gowne, &amp; dressed him like a scolar. Thā went he in to a certayne churchyard where he found a dead mans head, and than he toke the bead vp, &amp; made it cleane And whan it was cleane he bare it to a sertayn gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>smythe, and bad him that he shoulde bande the head with syluer bandes, &amp; he said that he would content him, &amp; so he did, Ind whā it was done: he contēted y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> goldsmyth, &amp; than departed he to a village nere ther by wher it was the dedicatiō day. And than came he to the parson of the churche &amp; saluted him, and than he told him y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he had a relyke, &amp; he prayd the curate y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he wolud do so muche for him: y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he wold shew it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the parish, that they myght offer to it. And he said to the person y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he shold haue the one halfe of the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. And than the parsō moued w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> couetise: graūted to hym, for he was glad to get mony. Than tolde he to the people of his parish. This man that here stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth hath brought a precious relike, he that offerth therto hath great pardon, He shall come into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet and declare it vnto you. Than went Howleglas into the pulpet, &amp; than told he the people of the relik that he had ther, &amp; he said that the head spake to him and that it bad him, that he shold bild a church ouer him and that the mone that the church should be bil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded with, should be wel gotten. And whā the mē and the women should come offer: than sayd Howleglas to the womē. Al those y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> haue made their husbandes
<pb facs="tcp:18452:15"/> cuckōlde should sit styll and come not to offer, for the hed bad hym that I should not receiue the offering, &amp; than he came down out of the pulpet, &amp; whan he was come down, than came the poore men &amp; ther wiues &amp; offered to the head. And ther was not on woman but she offered because that he had sayde so, and he gaue them the blessyng with the head, and there were som that had no mony, and they offered there rynges, and some of thē offered twyse or thryse, because y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> would be sene, and thei that were gilti presed first. And thus receyued he the offering both of the good &amp; of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yll, so that he had gotte a great som of mony by that sayde practyse. And whan thei had all offered, and that ther was no more that came: than he sayde to them. All ye men and women that here hath come, and offered to this head be honest and good and more ouer I charge you on payne of cursyng, that there be not on of you that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other slaundar or backbite, for if you had not bene good &amp; honest: I shoulde not haue receued your offerynge. And whan the poore men of they countrey hearyng Howleglas speake in this maner, they bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued hym. And whan the masse was done, thā came y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> parsone to Howleglas and sayd to hym, that he shold geue to hym halfe of the offeringe. And than deuided Howleglas the offeryng, and gaue the parson a parte therof, that the parsone was well content therewith And than departed Howleglas from the parson, and than the women ther a bout were veri glad of How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas &amp; made much of him. So abode he longe with them and spēt none of his mony, in such maner colde he cloke and hyde his vnhappinesse and falsenesse.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18452:15"/>
               <head>¶ How Howleglas came to the towne of Banberch and how he did eate for mony.</head>
               <p>VPō a tyme came Howleglas frō Norenbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough to banberce, where he entred in to a lodging, wher was a mery hostise, she had Howleglas often tymes welcome, for she sawe by his clothinge y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he was a mery gest. And as dyner tym came y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hostise asked him if that he would go to dener. and she asked him also if it pleased him to be at the twelue penie ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble. Than aunswered Howleglas and sayd, to his ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stice, I am but a poore man. I pray you for gods sake to geue me my dyner. Than sayd the hostise, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> baker and the butcher, wyll not be so payde. And therfore must I haue moni, for there is none in my house, but they eate and drinke all for mony. Than aunswered Howleglas, For mony do men eat and drinke in good fayth so wyl I? Than answered the woman to him. What table wyl you be at? For at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lordes table thei geue me no lesse than to shylinges, and at the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes table .xvi. pence, and at my houshold seruā<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes geue me twelue pence. Than aunswered Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alas to his hostyse. Sythe I must nedes eate and pai mony, thā geue me y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> best meate that you haue, And than he set him down at the lordes table. And thā his hostise brought to the table, the best meat. &amp; drinke y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> she had, and she had him make good cher, she sayd oft much good do it you gētel sir. And howleglas thāked his hostise many times. He eat &amp; drāke &amp; made hī wel at ease. And he eat so muche of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> good meat y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he swet againe. whan y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he had made hym well at ease, &amp; eatē and drunken al that he would: than bad he his hostise too auoyde the table, for he sayde he muste departe
<pb facs="tcp:18452:16"/> from thence. And right shortly at his cōmaundmēte the table was auoyded. And so he arose and stode by the fyre, &amp; whan he was thorowe warme he toke hys leue with his hostyce, &amp; would haue departed. That seyng the hostyss: toke hym by the sleue, &amp; bad him to geue her .ii. shyllynges for his dyner. Than answered he god thank you, for you haue remēbred me, I must haue two shyllynges of you. For you sayd to me, that there came no maner of persones within your house, but that the eat for mony. And whan you had tould me that: I sat me downe &amp; said, I would do the same. And I ate so muche that I swete again, and therfore you geue mony. Than saide his hostise, muste I geue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mony to eat my meat &amp; drinke my drink such gestes I may haue gret plēty. Pay me mi moni short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the bakers and bruers, will not be so āswered Than aunswered Howleglas to his hostise, geue me my mony, for thynkest thou that I wyll eate so much and laboure my selfe so fore as I dyd, not to be payd for mi laboure? yet I had much leuer neuer to haue sene y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> nor thy house, For I haue eaten so muche for mony, that mi belly, is lyke to burst, would you that I should haue such great laboure &amp; not to payd there fore? I haue other thynges to do, than to stande chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tīg here with the: and therfore come of lightly &amp; geue me my mony, and let me be gōe, for I haue right well deserued it. Than sayd his hostise to hym. Syr you ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue eaten my meate, and drōken mi drinke, and bi my fyre, you haue had your ease, and all at your owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre, wherfore I praye you to geue me mony. And he aunswered ryght angerly. woulde y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> haue me to paye mony, and I dyd eate therefore, thei whiche is to my
<pb facs="tcp:18452:16"/> great harme? Thā she āswered to Howleglas, if your eatyng do you harme, I am not the cause therof but your eatyng is to my losse, not onely that I haue lost more than that cometh to. And than she saide depart thou fro my house and neuer after this y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thou be so bold once to enter within my dores. Than sayd How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>legas, wil you on your conscience take mi labour for nothyng: well fare well. And than departed Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas, and he was glad that he had so scaped fro her, &amp; she was glad that she was so delyuered of hym.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas went to Rome to speke with the Pope.</head>
               <p>THan whan Howleglas had longe occupyed hys falsenes: thā he remembred this old prouerbe. I will to Rome mi maners to amende: &amp; home agaīe my lyfe for to ende. And than departed he too Rome, where he shewed parte of his vngraciousnes, &amp; whā he came to Rome, he lodged with a wydow and they wydowe did ofte beholde him in the face and because he was a fayre yong man: she saed oftētymes, sir you be ryght well come. Good syr she sayde from whence be you? I am of Sasson: and my coming hether is for to speake with the Pope. Than answered she to How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas good frende you may see him: but you shal not speake with hym. For I y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> am borne in Rome, woulde haue geue an .C. ducates to speake to hī, but I could neuer speake to him. Than sayd Howleglas. Hostyse will you geue an .C. ducates: and I shall bring you to to the speche of the pope? And she sware to him bi her faith she would, for otherwise it would cost her more in gyftes. Thā on a time should the pope syng masse his owne persone, at saynt Ihon Lat eraū. For euery
<pb facs="tcp:18452:17"/> fowre wekes he must sing masse there. And as y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pope was at masse: than Howleglas drew nere to the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And whan the pope was at the holy sacramente: than tourned Howleglas his back to the aulter. And that seyng all the cardinalles, whan masse was done the came to the pope, and the tolde to his grace, that there stode a fayre younge man, all the whyle that ye were at masse, and harde it deuoutly tyll the time of the leuacion. And whā that you lifted vp the chalyce aboue your head: than tourned he his backe toward the sacramente of the aulter. Than sayde the pope, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is a thyng to be loked on, for it is a great dobte whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that mā beleue well or not. And therfore it is ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>defull for vs to sende for that man, &amp; to examin hym what errour it was that he helde. the cardinalles and<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swered, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> were the best. than the pope sende for How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leglas to his Inne: and y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> messanger brought him to- the pope. and whan he came before the pope, &amp; the car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinalles, they began strayghtly to examyne hym and they asked of hym, what was his belefe? than answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Howleglas to the pope. I beleue as a true christē mā ought for to beleue. And I beleue in Iesu christe. and I beleue in that, that our holi mother the church doth teach me, and I beleue as my good hostise dothe beleue, and he named her before the pope, and al that noble congregacion. And than sent y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pope a messēger to the Inne, where y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> Howleglas was lodged, &amp; whan he was there, he came to the hostise &amp; bad her that she shold make her ready, for she must nedes go with him to the pope. wherof she had great marueile, and made her redy and so went with him to the pope. And whan she was come before thei pope, he asked her what her
<pb facs="tcp:18452:17"/> belefe was. And she answered to the pope. Reuerend father, I beleue as a true christen woman should do. For I beleue as the holy churche beleues, and also I beleue in al that the holy churche bindes me to. Thā said Howleglas the same beleue I. Than the pope as<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked him, why he turned his backe to the holy sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whan he did minister it? Than sayde Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas to the pope. Reuerende father in god, I thought in my mynde whan that you lyft vp the blessed sacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, that I was not worthy it to beholde, nor there on to loke, tyll the tyme that I was confessed, &amp; made cleane of all my synnes. And than was the pope with that answere marueilously well contented and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, And after that the pope bad him that he shold cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse him of his synnes, and to make him clene therof and that sayd: he gaue his benediction to Howleglas and his hostyse, &amp; so they twaine departed. And short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after departed the pope with all his cardinalles in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the palayce, and so Howleglas was quyte therof.</p>
               <p>And than sayd Howleglas to his hostise I must haue my, C. ducates that I haue erned. And than the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man gaue him the .C. ducates, whereof he was glad, and he sayd to his selfe that he was y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> better for that Iourney to Rome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas deceyued the Iewes with durte.</head>
               <p>WHan Howleglas the great deceyuer had bene at Rome: than came he to the towne of Frāke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forde, where a marte or a greate market was kepte. And as Howleglas went about the market: he spyed a younge man goe with muske of Alexander to sell, that whyche was well solde and muche sette by.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18452:18"/>
               <p>Than sayde Howleglas to his selfe, I wyll goo with some marchaundise for to sell, as well as that yonge mā doth. And he thought in his mind, how he might fynd sōe practese to get mony without labour. Thā thought he in his mynde euery nyght what was best to do, for the flene did bite hym, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he coulde not slepe. And he would ryght gladly haue taken them: but he could not. And when that the daye began to sprīg he arose and walked forth and as he walked, than spied he by the way a fayre fyg tree, the which bare goodly fruyte. And thā went he and gathered two or thre of them, and than he sayde to him selfe this is good for my marchaundyse and brought them with hym into Frankforth in Portyngale, to the place wher he was lodged and he dressed them after his mind. And whā he had dressed them: he put them in his arse and tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pered them with his durte, and let them lye thereby hym, by the space of .ii. or .iii. dayes, that they should not smell to much of durte. And in a mornyng by ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes he arose oute of his bed, &amp; wente to his hostyse &amp; hyred a litle table, &amp; than he went into the market, &amp; bought two or thre silken clothes, and therin a house he crussed these portingales fygges, that had lyen so longe in his arse: withe they silken clothes, lyke as it had bene the must. Than toke he his table and wente into they market, and set vp his table. And whan it was vp than shewed he the portyngale fygges, that he had made like as it had bene must. Thā came ther many marchantes of diuers landes to hym, and thei asked hym what marchaundyse he had to sell: and he stode stel and gaue none of them no answere, wher of the marueyled, and so departed. And at they laste:
<pb facs="tcp:18452:18"/> there came to him two Iewes, &amp; the asked hym what marchaundyse he had there to sell? and than answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Howlegas to them, and sayde. This is a precious thīg, for all those that do eate of it, or those that smell to it, they shall sae the trouthe by and by. Than went the Iewes to counsaill what was best to be dōe Thā sayde the oldeste Iewes of them all. Me thynke it is best and moste expedient for vs to bie that marchaū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyse, for than shal we know whan that our Messyas shall come therfore I counsayle you to bye it, for it shalbe to vs a great Iowel &amp; comfort and continent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they were a greed al, for to bye the marchaūdyse of Howleglas, And thā the returned w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> right great hast vnto Howleglas. And whan they were come: they as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the price of on of the Prophetus that was wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the sylke. than aunswered Howleglas to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes, Departe fro hence, and let my marchaundyse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, for it is to costly for you to bye: for one of them shall cost you .v.C. goulde gyldens, and ye will haue it than aunswered the Iewes to Howleglas and sayde. the pryce is all to great for vs: than said he, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I tolde you before and therfore if thou wyll not bie it, thā de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parte shortly from hence, And than the Iewes hering Howleglas speake so sharpely to them, and made no more count vnto them: than then beleued him, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently they gaue to him .v.C. gold gildens without speaking of any more wordes, for he spake so angerly that they were a frayde to displease hym. And whan they had bought it: they brought it too the principall Iewe. And the caused him to aggregate all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Iewes, both olde and young when the were assembled: than was there one stode vpon the scaffolde, that was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:18452:19"/> Akypna. And he sayde that be the mighte of God they had gottē a Prophetus and he said he that shold haue it in his mouth should prophecie the truth, and than he sayd to the Iewes. By this prophetus we shall know when our Messias shal come. And he com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded them to fast thre dayes. And than should I<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>saake take it in his mouth, &amp; prophecy the truth, and so he did. And as he had it in his mouthe, on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hyghte Maysayes, and an other Isaac that were the seruaū<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of god they asked hym howe it sauoured? and he answered I am inspired with the holy ghoste, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy the truth. There must be an other of gods ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaūtes to haue it in his mouth, and so they dyd, whā he had tasted therof he sayde: I ame inspyred with the holy ghost. I shall tel you the truthe, we are begylede for it is noo ther thynge but a turde, and they tasted and the turde hāged in theyr tethe, wich the here that he had cut fro his arse, and than they knew well that they were deceyued. And forthwith departed Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas fro thence, and he went toward his owne coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye, and made good chere with good felowes home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde. as long as the mony would last.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas had gotten the parsons horse, by his confession.</head>
               <p>IN Resendring in that villag was a parsō, that hade a fayre horse, and a proper handemayden which he loued one as the other: than it fortūed that the duke of Bronsewyke on a tyme sawe the horse, &amp; whan y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he had sene the horse: his mind rane so muche on the horse, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he must nedes haue hym. Than vpō a tyme cam the duke, and desired the horse oftentimes of the parson, &amp; the parson sayd him nay. Than was
<pb facs="tcp:18452:19"/> the duke sory because he might not haue the horse, &amp; he durst not take by forse: for he was one of the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sayll of Broneswika. And whan Howleglas harde y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the duke desyred the horse: than said Howleglas to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> duke, &amp; you wyll rewarde me, I shall get you the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sons horse. Thā aunswered the duke to Howlegas. I shal geue the my gowne of red chamblet, the on sleue set with pearles. Than said Howleglas to the duke, I shal bryng him I haue no doubt. So departd How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas, and he came to the Inne, where he was well knowē, &amp; the hoste sayde he was welcome. And Howe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas rested there thre dayes, and after that he made himself sicke. Than was he brought to bed sick that the parson of the towne &amp; his mayde were so heuy, &amp; knew not how to dō nor him to helpe. And than begā he to waxe sicker &amp; sicker, And than said the parson to Howleglas. I counsaill you to be shreuen, ād to take your rightes of the holly church, as it belongeth to a true christen mā. And whan howleglas hard the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sone speke to him. Than sayde Holeglas to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> parsone I desyre you hartefully to be confessed, for I knowe my selfe giltie, and a great sinner. Than the parson ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amined him vnder confessione right buselye, he bad him to remember that he had a soule for to kepe, and he preached and teached to hym the vse of confession And than shewed Howleglas to hyme, parte of hys mynde. And at the laste whan he spake no more: than asked the parson of Howleglas if that he had no more synnes in his mynde that were great and abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that he was ashamed to shewe. Than aunswered Howleglas to the parsone yes, I haue our more and that I dare not confesse me of to you, and therefore
<pb facs="tcp:18452:20"/> you must fetche me an other priest: for if I shold shew it vnto you, than would ye be angry &amp; out of paciēce Than answered the parson to Howleglas and saide: the wai is far from this place and very foule. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer if it fortuned you in the meane whyle to dye thā were we both in great peryll &amp; daunger. And therfor tell me that sinne, &amp; I shal absolue the therof, be it ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer so great &amp; abhominable. And if I wer angry with you, yet you knowe I must kepe your counsaill. And if it be any thinge that longes to me, I for geue you frely, and therfore tel it me. Thā longed he more thā euer he did, thā said Howleglas to the priest. I knowe well that you wyl be angry, but I fele me so soresick that I wene that I shal dye, and therfore I shal shew it to you quickely. And than he saide, I haue lyen by your mayde your seruaunt. Than asked he how oftē haue ye lyen by her? And than sayde Howleglas, no more than fiue times. And than the priest thought in his mind, therfore the deuill breake thy necke, and he gaue hym absoluciō shortly, and forth with he depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted fro Howleglas whome to his house. And whan he came home, he called his maydē to him, and asked her if she had lyne by hym? And the mayde aunswered to hym and sayd: that dyd I neuer. Than answered the pryest, thou lyest. For vnder confession he hath tolde me that he hath lyen bi the, more than .v. times. And than the mayde sayd naye, and the priest yes. And thā the priest toke a staffe in his hand and he bet his maid therewith, that she was both blacke and blewe. And Howleglas laye in his bedde and laughed, and said to himselfe. Now weneth the priest to wyn hys shone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne of the mayd, And in the morning wexed How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas
<pb facs="tcp:18452:20"/> hole, and arose and sayde it was wel amended with him. And he asked his hostise &amp; the priest, what he had spend in his sicknes? And than rekened the priest he knewe nat what, for he was so angry in his mynde and the maid also, for she was beate for his sake. And than sayd Howleglas. Tell me what is my duty to paye? And the priest aunswered not a word. And than said Howleglas to him. Remember you not mayster parson that you haue disclosed my confession? I shal ryde to hauerstad to the byshop and I shal complaine on you: that you discried my confession that I cōfes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed me vnto you. Whan y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> priest hard Howleglas spek after that maner: than forgot he his anger, and fel on his knees before hym, for he thought that he was in more daunger than euer he was before. And than he sayd to Howleglas, if that you will kepe your peace and make no more wordes herof, I shall geue to you twenty golde gildens, and I shall do as much for you as lyes in me for to be done. Than made Howleglas hymselfe very angry with the parsone, and said vnto hym. If that you would geue me an .C. gold gildens, that I should not shewe: I will not take them for my gowne. Than the priest preyed the mayde with we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping teares, that she would go to Howleglas &amp; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat hym, that he should not go to shewe the bishop, and byd hym aske what he wyll, and he shall haue it. Than went the mayd to Howleglas, and she shewed him what the priest saide. And than came Howleglas to the priest and sayd. Wyl you geue to me your horse that you loue so wel, and than shal I kepe your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayle? And I tel you plainly, I wil haue no other thīg than that only. And than the prieste was more soryer
<pb facs="tcp:18452:21"/> than euer he was. And he sayd to Howleglas, that hel would geue to him as much moni as he would desire and not to aske his horse. Thā said Howleglas. I wil haue none other thing but only the hors. And thā the parson had leuer loose his horse, than he would haue the bishop to knowe. Than gaue he the horse to How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas withe ill wyll. And than whan Howleglas had the horse, than he departed fro the parsone, and was very glad. And than he came towarde the duke. And whan he was come there, the duke spyed Howleglas and the parsons hors: than was he very glad. And thā brought Howleglas the horse to him, wherof he was very glad. And than gaue he the gowne of red cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blet to Howleglas, and he thanked hym greately for that gyft and laughed, and the priest was very angry for thei losse of his horse, and oftentymes he bete his mayden therfore, for he sayd she was the cause therof And he bete his mayd so oft, that at the laste she rann from him, and so he lost both his horse and the mayde And the priest lowred on Howleglas euer after, that loued hem so well before.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas was hyred of a blacke smyth.</head>
               <p>AT Dastland in Rosticke dwelleth a smith y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Howleglas for his man, and whā he was hyred: he put him to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bellowes to blowe. And whan he blew not well, than toke the smith the bellowes in his hande and blewe: and sayd felowe doo thus. Bere the bellowes vpright and than he gaue y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> belowes to Howleglas agayne. than wente the smyth forth with into the garden, and than tooke Howleglas the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes on his necke, and folowed after his maister with thē into the garden where his maister was a shytinge and than sayde Howleglas to his mayster, wher shall
<pb facs="tcp:18452:21"/> I leue this belowes y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I may go fetch the other vnto you. Than answered his maister and sayd, good man what meanest thou, art y<seg rend="sup">u</seg> not wel in thy mynd? Goo take the belowes and bare them where thou had thē he spake fayre to Howleglas, and ryght lothe he was to displease him. For euery nyght by the space of viii dayes long, he called vp euery night his seruaūts at mydnight for to worke, wherof they marueiled what he ment, for they were very angry therwith: and one sayd to the other. I thynke our maister is not well in his mind, that he ryses euery night at mydnight to worke, he was not wont so for to doo in tymes paste: And as they were speakyng of this rysyng together, thā said Howleglas to his felowes &amp; asked thē if that they would be wel content with hym, and if he asked of his maister what was the cause that he dydde call them vp euery nyght at midnight to worke? And thā aunswered the seruauntes, we wel not be displeased therwith, but right glade therof, and well contente therewith, &amp; than sayd Howleglas to the seruauntes I wyll go to him. And forth with spake Howleglas to his mayster and sayd to him. Wherfore do ye wake vs euery night at mydnight oute of our slepe. Than aunswered the smyth and sayd. That is my maner that my men the first eyght dayes suffer I not thē to, slepe, but halfe the nyght. Than held Howleglas hys peace, and all his felowes, and sayde noo more woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and the next night the smyth called his menn at mydnyght to worke. And Howleglas than tooke the bed and bare it on his backe, and whan the yron was hote the maister bet it se hard, that the speckes flew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edde of Howleglas, Than sayde his mayster
<pb facs="tcp:18452:22"/> wil not that vngracious felow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ise: Thā cāe How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas with his bed on his back. And whan the mayi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster saw the bed on his backe, he said: what wilt thou do with the bed? Bere it into the place wher thou had it. Than aunswered Howleglas to his maister, be ye not angri w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> me: for this is mi maner euer. For whan that I haue slept the ōe halfe of the nyght, than bere I the bed on my backe thei other halfe of the nyghte. Than began the smyth to waxe angry and sayde, Go bere the bed wher thou had it and thā go thou aboue oute of my house. Than aunswered Howleglas and sayde maister with a good will. And than he bare thei bed vp into the place wher it was before. Than whā he had borne the bed in his place: than toke he a ladre and clymed vp to the house top, &amp; ther he brake a gret hole in the house top: and pulled away the thatchyng therof, and he passed through and went ouer the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses and so went his wai from thence, and neuer came there after. And as the smyth was bese workyng: the harde a great noyse about in the chamber and a gret knockyng. Than asked he his seruauntes, who was aboue in the chambre that made such a noyse? Than answered the men to their maister and sayd we know not who is aboue. Than sayd the smyth, than will I go loke. And than left the smyth his worke and wente vp into the chamber, and whan he was aboue, he saw al the roofe of the chamber was pulled downe, and al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>so caste all aboute, than was he angrye and wyst not what to do for he wiste not who had done it. And at the laste he looked vp and spyed the ladre, than knewe He well that it was Howleglas dede. Than came he downe and fetched a sworde, and he would haue run
<pb facs="tcp:18452:22"/> after him to haue slayne hym. Than the seruauntes seyng the maister takyng the sworde they helde him, and asked him what he woulde do: Than aunswered he &amp; tolde how Howleglas had dane. Than aūswered the seruaūtes to ther maister. Let him go for he hath done as you bad hym, for you bad hym goo vpon the house, and so he hath done as ye maye see. And so thei smyth was cōtent. And thā he caused his house to be newe thatched agayne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas was hyred of a shomaker.</head>
               <p>VPon a tyme serued Howleglas a shomaker, and vpō a tyme the shomaker had busynes ī y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> towne, &amp; thā gaue he to Howleglas a hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de of lether, &amp; bad him y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he shold cut all the hyde. And Howleglas asked him what facion he should cut thē. And the maister said litle and great, as the swineherd dyd driue his beastes. And than sayd Howleglas with a good will. And than departed the cordiner: and than toke Howleglas the hide, and began to cut the lether for oxen and shepes fete, and swyne. Than came his maister home, and came to see what his seruaunt had cut out and to loke whether he had cut the lether as he bad hym. And whan that he had sēe, that he had cut out his lether all in beastes clawes, than was he angry and sayde to Howleglas? wherfore haste thou marrēd all my lether, and cut it for beastes fete. Thā aunswered he to him and sayd. I haue done as ye bad me. The maister sayde thou leest, for I bad they that thou should not marre my lether. Than aunswered Howleglas to his maister and sayde, I haue doone as ye bad me, ye bad we that I should cut both gret and small, as the swneherde dryueth out his beastes, and
<pb facs="tcp:18452:23"/> than haue I done. Than aunswered the cordyner to Howleglas &amp; sayde. I ment not that: I mente that ye should haue cut out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hyde bothe great shoene and lytle shoene. Thā aunswered Howleglas to his maister. If that ye had tolde me it before: I woulde haue done it with a good wyll. And I praye you mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster forgeue me this: &amp; I shall nowe do it with a good wyll and than dyd his mayster forgeue hym, for that tyme: and than promysed Howleglas to hys mayster, that he would do that, that he bad hym. Thā the next daye after cut Howleglas mayster himselfe, y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> shoene out both lytle and great, &amp; gaue them to hym, and he bad hym that he should sowe the great with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> small: and Howleglas sayde with a good wyll, and than to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke Howleglas the shoene, and put the lytle shoene in to the great shoene, and sowed thē both together, as his maister bad hym, and that spyed his mayster: and sayde. ye be a good seruaunt for ye do al thyng that I byd you. Than aūswered Howleglas and saide. Thei that do as the be byd: the be worthy to haue thanke. Than saide the maister, ye do after mi saying and not after my meanyng. For I meane that first ye shoulde haue sowed a lytle payre, and after a great payre. And the maister was hasty, and toke him other lether and sayde, Cut me all this lether vpon one laste. And they maister thoughte no more of they falsenes of Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas, and so he departed to his chamber, and whan he was come home, thā remembred he what he had sayd to Howleglas. Than went he as fast as he coulde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde they shop where as Howleglas was, and or he came there, Howleglas had cut all the lether, vpon y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lytle laste, all for the left fote. Than whan his maister
<pb facs="tcp:18452:23"/> sawe all his lether cut for the left foote, than asked he Howleglas if there belonged not to thei lefte foote a ryght foote, and he was very angry with hym. Than sayde Howleglas to his maister. If that he had tolde to me before: I would haue cut them, but &amp; it please you, I shall cut as mani right shoene vnto them. The maister sayde. I bad the cutte the one with the other and than aunswered Howleglas. ye bad me cutte all vpon one laste. Than aunswered the shoemaker. It that I should kepe you long: you woulde make me so poore that I muste nedes goe a beggyng. But nowe geue me mony for my lether y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> thou haste marred me, and departe thou fro hence. Than aunswered How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leglas to the shoemaker. The hyde of a bul wyl make two hydes. And with those wordes he arose and sayde In this house haue I bene, but I wyll not come here agayne, and so departed he fro thence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas solde turdes for fat.</head>
               <p>ANd as Howleglas had destroyed much lether of the Shoemaker, wherof the Shoemaker was very sory, and that heryng Howleglas, returned agayne to the towne, and came to his maister, &amp; tolde hym that he had a last of talowe, and he tolde his mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster that he shoulde haue it good chepe, for too restore hym parte of the harme, that he had doone to him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his lether. And than the shoemaker sayde yf it be good: I pray you let me haue it before another. And than saide Howleglas with a good wyll, And thā departed they, and than went howleglas to the gong fermers. &amp; made hym fill twelue barells with turdes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or a lytle mony, and than toke he a lytle talowe, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t in the barels fowre ynches thycke, as though it
<pb facs="tcp:18452:24"/> had ben altogether grece, and closed it so close that it could not stynke. For it was in the wynter whan ther was a great frost, that the durte was fast frosen to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> barell, and the other syxe barells he filled with other, talowe or fat more thycker than the other syxe were, for they were the example of his marchaundyse. And whan that he had dressed all the barelles he sende for his maister they shoemaker, and he asked hym, if y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he would come to see the marchaundyse. And he sayd he would. Than within a whyle came the shoemaker to howleglas, and when he was come there, Howleglas made the heades of the best barells, to be droken vp. whan the cordener sawe the barelles they lyked hym very wel. And than howleglas asked him how the ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rels pleased hym and he answered very well. And thā asked he the pryce. And than aūswered howleglas ye shall geue me no more than fowre and twenty gyldēs xii. in hand, &amp; the other twelue at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> yeres end. And thā was the shoemaker content, and thought no deceyte and gaue to him .xii, gildens in hande. And howleglas receyued the mony, and than departed he. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyner was glad of thei bargayne, and thought that y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> foresayde harme that he had dōe hym, should be resto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red. And than the hyred a seruaunt to melt the talow and he brought one barell by the fyre, and whan they durt began to waxe hote it began to smell. Than said the one to the other. I wene some of vs hath beshittē, their breches. And than came the maister &amp; bad them make cleane theyr shoene, for on of you hath trodē in a tourde, and than they loked about, but the founde nothyng. And than shoulde the haue put one of they barelles in the caudrene, than sawe they well that it
<pb facs="tcp:18452:24"/> was the barrell that stank, for it was full of tourdes And than they left their work, and went for to seeke Howleglas, but he was gone: and so the shoemaker must suffer the laste losse with the first.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas serued a tayler.</head>
               <p>ON a tyme serued Howleglas a taylar, &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler asked him, if y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he coulde sowe woll a clothe, that no man might se the seame. And thā said Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas yes. And than went Howleglas &amp; sowed vnder a barrell. Thā said his maister what doest thou now this is a maruelous sowing. Than aunswered How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leglas, I sow so close that no man can see as you bad me nor I mi selfe se not. than aunswered his maister good seruaunt I ment not so: I bad the sow that eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry man might see And than the thyrde night the mai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ster had labored so sore, that he must nedes slepe. thā caste he to Howleglas, a husbande mans gowne, and he bad him take a wolfe &amp; make it vp. And than sayd Howleglas I shall do it. Than wēt he to bed. Than cut Howleglas the husbandmans gown, and made therof a woulffe with the head and feete. And whan that he had sowed it together, than set he it vpon the table wythe staues. than in they mornynge arose his maister, and came down, and whā he saw the woulfe standynge vpon the table he was a frayde: and asked hym what he had done. And he saide mayster: I haue made a woulfe as you bad me. than sayd the maister. I ment that you should haue made vp y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> russet gown for a husband mans gowne is called here a woulfe.</p>
               <p>than aunswered Howleglas. If that I had knowen that before I would haue dōe so, For I had leuer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue made a gowne than a woulfe. And at the last was
<pb facs="tcp:18452:25"/> they maister contente. And within fowre dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, watched they mayster so muche that he muste nedes goo to sleepe. And there was a cote readye made, but it lacked the sleues. Thā the maister toke the cote and the sleues and gaue them to Howleglas and he bad hym that he should cast on the sleues, and he sayd he would. Than went his maister to bed, and than toke Howleglas the cote &amp; hanged it on a balke and set on euery syde a candle, and stode vp &amp; cast the sleues at the cote all thei nyght long. And thā arose y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tailer and that spied howleglas, and he cast the sleues more faster than euer he did before at the cote. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> aspyed wel the taylar, &amp; sayd what folishe touches be those y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you do ther. And thā answered howleglas ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry angerly. This is no folish touche for I haue stande all the nyghte castinge the sleues at the cote, and they will not abyde theron, and nowe I se it is but loste la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour. Than sayd they mayster to houleglas. It is my faute for I wend y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ye would haue vnderstand me bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for I mēt you should haue sowed on the sleues on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cote. Thā said howleglas to his maister. The deuyl take you, for if ye had said so to me before: I might ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue sowed on the sleues, &amp; haue gon to slepe. But now maister go you &amp; sowe al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> day long, &amp; I will go slepe. And than aunswered the tailer, &amp; haue I hired you to slepe? And thus began they to chyde. And as the wer thus chiding: the taylar bad hympay for his candels, that he had brenned that night. And than Howleglas spake neuer a worde more but tooke all his clothes &amp; went his way and came no more there.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas throughe his settle disceytes, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued a wyne drawer in Lubeke.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18452:25"/>
               <p>ON a tyme came Howleglas to Lubeke, where is very straight Iustice, &amp; the while that How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leglas was there a bidyng: he herd tell of a wyne dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer that was in a lordes seller, that was very proud and presumptuous. And it was saide that there was no man that could deceiue hī, nor passe him in wisdō and there was none of all the lordes that loued hym. Than thought Howleglas in his mynde, howe he myght deceyue hym than vpon a tyme toke Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas two pottes, one of water, and thei other empty, and he hid the empty pot that no man saw it &amp; he cāe to the seller &amp; gaue the wyne drawer the emty pot, &amp; bad him fill the pot with wyne, &amp; so he dyd. And whan it was full he broughte it vp to howleglas, and than he loked a side &amp; in the meane whyle howleglas set y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pot of water in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> place of wine &amp; hid the pot of wyne. And than asked he y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wyne drawer what he shuld pay And the drawer sayd .x. miten. than sayde howleglas the wine is to dere for me, I haue but .viii. mitē than was the drawer angry, &amp; sayde wyll ye sette an other pryce on the wyne than the lordes haue set? thā sayd howleglas I haue no more monye, &amp; I shall not haue it so, than take your wyne agayne for I knewe it not before. than was they wyne drawer very angry, and he toke the pot with the water, and bare it down īto the seller: and poured out the water into the vessel &amp; he wende it had bene the wine, and came &amp; gaue how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas the pot, and sayd. Make ye me fyll wyne, and ye haue no mony to paye for it: ye wene ye be a foole? And than sayde howleglas ye be begyled of a foole, and with that woorde he wente his waye wyth they pottes. And than the drawer mistrustyng howleglas
<pb facs="tcp:18452:26"/> for the wordes that he sayde, toke a sergeaunt and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer toke hym, and fetched hym, and than they found that he had two pottes vnder the mātell. Than toke the Howleglas and peched him for a thefe, &amp; brought hym to the pryson. And than sayd some, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he had deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to be hanged and some saide that it was done for the nonse to deceiue the wine drawer, &amp; that was but well done for he shoulde haue se there to before. for he sayde dayly that no man should begyle hym: but they that loued not Howleglas sayde that he was a thefe, &amp; that he shoulde be hanged. And thā was Howleglas brought before the Iudge, and the gaue sentēce, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hy shold be hanged. And on the morowe was he brought vnto the gallowes, for to be hanged. for they that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued hym not, would fayne haue sene Iustice done on hym. And there were gathered many of the towne to see Howleglas suffer death. But they Lordes of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kibe were sory for hym, for some wende that he could do wychcrafte, that he thereby myght be delyuered. And as he was led towarde the galowes, he lay al styl as though he had ben dead. And whan he came vnder the gallowes, than desired he to speke with the lordes And whan the lordes were, com he fell vpō his knees and he prayed them that the wold graunt him abone and the lordes sayde. Thou woldest desyre thy pardō. Than sayd Howleglas. That would I not aske lyfe nor mony, nor it shall not cost you one peny. Than all the lordes of Lubeke went to the other side of the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and there they layde theyre heades together, &amp; there the rehersed his wordes againe, and the agreed to graunt hym his peticion. That done they came to hym and the bad him aske what he would, saue those
<pb facs="tcp:18452:26"/> wordes spoken of before to be except. And howleglas thanked the lordes and sayde. I praye you that euery one of you geue me your handes therof. And they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together gaue him their handes, so that all the lordes had graunted him both with worde and hand. Than sayd Howleglas to the lordes. Because I know you be faythfull of your wordes, I shall shewe to you my bone. And than he said this is my boone. That euery lorde of Lubeke do come &amp; kisse mi arse, whan that I haue hāged on the galowes by the space of thre daies long, with his mouth in the morning fastinge and the borow maister firste, and all the lordes after in ordre. Than aunswered the lordes to Howleglas and sayd, that his desyre was an vnmanerly boone for to be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. And than sayde Howleglas to they lordes of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beke I kdowe the counsail of Lubeke, so sure of their promyse that they wil holde that that they haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mysed me both with hande and mouthe. Than went the lordes agayne to counsaele. than sayde they one to the other this thynge that he asketh of vs it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully asked, for it were a greate shame for vs all, that we that be the gretest lordes of the town, should cōe and kisse his arse: better it were for to geue hym his pardon, and let hym goo hys waye, for it ys but a small faute that he hath done. than agreed all they lordes and sayde that it was best for to do. than the lordes called the sergeauntes, and they bad them too vnbynde Howleglas and to let hym goe at large, for, all they had graunted hym his pardon. And than they vnlosed Howleglas. And whan Howlegles was at large, he thanked the Lordes. And than departed he from Lubeke, and neuer came there after.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18452:27"/>
               <head>¶ How Howleglas became a maker of spectacles, &amp; howe he could fynde no worke in no lande where he came.</head>
               <p>ON a tyme the senatours of Rome, had gret dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord among them selfe, which of all the lordes shoulde be Emperoure. And at the last was y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earle of Supplembrogh kyng of Romaynes and Emperour of Rome, but thee were mani other that loked for it. So whan he was made, he lay .vi. wekes long before the towne of Frankforde, abydyng ther for all other, lordes to tormēt, where was a great company assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. And this hering Howleglas, he thoughte in hys minde to go thether. &amp; so he did. And there he thought to get some gyfte. And it wer no more but the Empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perours syluer harnes. And as Howleglas passed by Frankforde he met with the bysshop of Taer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he was clothed auenture lyke, he asked hym, what he was? than aūswered Howleglas. I am a spec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacle maker come out of Braband, and I can find no worke. Than sayde the bysshop, me thinke your craft shoulde be better daylye, for the people y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> longer they lyue thei lesse syghte they haue therfore youre crafte shoulde be the better. And than said Howleglas to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> byshop, my lorde you say truth but there is one thīge that destroyed our craft: and if you wil take no disple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sure, I shall shewe it to you. And than y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bysshop bad, hym saye what he woulde. And than sayde he, this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyeth our craft, that suche great lordes as you be, kynges, dukes, erles, lordes bysshopps, knyghtes, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyers, and gouernours of l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>̄des and townes, al these looke through their fyngers, and not with spectacles They were wont to study in the olde tyme the ryghte
<pb facs="tcp:18452:27"/> and than behoued the mē many spectacles. And also the priestes, were wonte to stude and reade their ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice but now they vse no spectacles at al and by this maner is our craft destroyed and nought set by. And by heades of the countrey that poore men of the coū<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree learne all to loke thorowe their handes that they be almoste as cunning, as the heades of the coūtrey. Thā the byshop vnderstode the text but not the glose and he spake to Howleglas and sayde. come with me to Frankeforde, and I shall geue vnto the my harnes or clothyng, and than was Howlyglas veri glad and he wente with the byshop to Frankeforde, where the Emperour was chosen: and whan thei trumphe was done that the beshop gaue hī that that he promysed hym, and than was he glad and he wente with the by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>shop, and so he returned agayne to Sassen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas was hyred of a merchaunt. to be his coke</head>
               <p>AT Heldersem dwelled a marchaunt, that on a tyme went walkyng without the town, and as he walked: he founde Howleglas lyinge on a grene hyll. Than asked the marchaūt Howleglas wha the was? Howleglas answered vnder his couered falsnes I am a cooke, and without a maister, Than said the marchaunt: yf you wyll be a good seruaunte, I wyll hyre you, and geue vnto you wages, I haue a cooke, at home: but my wyfe complayneth on hym alwaye. Than promysed Howleglas the marchaunte to bee true to hym. Than asked the marchaunte his name, than aunswered howleglas, my name is Bartholo, mens. Than sayd the marchaunt, that name is al to longe: youre name shall be Dole, than sayde howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas, I holde me contented therewith. Than sayde
<pb facs="tcp:18452:28"/> the marchaunt. Dole my man, nowe let vs go gether some herbes for yoūg chekhins, for to morow I must haue gestes to dyner: and than went the home to hys place together. And whan the marchauntes wyfe sawe Howleglas she asked her husbande: what shall we do with this mā, wene you that oure bread moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des? Than sayde the merchaunt. Be contente wyfe, this shalbe your man for he is a coke. Than called he his man and sayd. Dole take a basket and folowe me to the fleshe shambles, and so he dyd. And whan they were there the marchaunt bought meat for to roste, and whan he came home, he called his man and sayde Dole to morowe lay the meate to the fyre, and rost it coldly y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ye burne it not: and Howleglas sayd he wold, and than he arose in the mornynge, and broughte the meate by the fyre, and he toke the meat that he shold roste and put it on the spytte, &amp; bare it down into the seller, and he layde it betwene two barelles of bere, that it shold lye colde ynough, and burne not. And be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cause the marchaūt shold haue gestes, he came home, before to see whether that his meate was well rosted or not. And whan he came home, he called Dole, and asked him, if that they meate was ready: and Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas answered, ye maister al saue the rostinge. Where haste thou done it? benethe in the seller, betwene two barrelles, for in all the house could I not fynd so cold, a place to laie it in for burnyng. The marchaunt said is it not rosted? and howleglas sayde naye, for I dyd as ye bad me, I layd it cold ynoughe for I knewe not the tyme that you woulde haue had it rosted: and as the were talking together came in the gestes, and the marchaunt tolde to hys gestes howe that howleglas
<pb facs="tcp:18452:28"/> had serued him, and the laughed therat, but his wife was not content therwith and ryght gladly she wold haue bene rede of hym, &amp; very angri she was because of that touche. Than sayd the merchaunt to his wife Be contented at this tyme, for to morow I muste to hassaer and he shall wayte on me: and whan I shall come home agayne, than shall I pute hym awaye fro hence: and than went the merchaunt with his gestes to dyner and made good chere and at nyght called the marchaūt his man and sayde. Dole make the wagen ready, for to morow I am in thought, I and mi priest to take our Iourney to haslaer, and grease it that it may go trym: and than went Howleglas and greased the wagen within and without, and in the mornynge went the marchunt and thei priest to the wagen, and rode their waye: and by the waye, the priest layde hes hande on the rayles of they carte, and they made hys handes all greasy: and than he loked better, and both the marchaunt &amp; the priest were al arayed with grese Than they called Howleglas, and the bad him se, and very angrye they were with him, &amp; in the mean tyme came there a man of the countrey with a lod of straw and than they boughte parte of hys strawe, &amp; dressed their wagen therwith for fylyng of their clothes and than they wente vnto the wagen agayn than said the marchaunt all angerly. Go driue it vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> galowes and as he was a litle further he spyed a galowes, and thither droue he the wagen vnder the galowes: and whan it was vnder the galowes, he made the wagen to stande styll, &amp; he vntyed thei horse. Than sayde the marchaunt what wyll you nowe do? than sayde How ieglas: tari you here al night, for you bad me to driue
<pb facs="tcp:18452:29"/> you vnder the galowes. And whan they saw that the were vnder the galowes: the prieste laughed, but the marchaūt was veri angri, and bad him to driue forth ryght, and neuer to stand stil. Than said Howleglas, he would, than pulled he out a pyn that was in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gen that helde it fast to the horse, and droue the horse forth and he left them vnder the galowes. Than the marchaūt seyng that he lept out of the wagen, &amp; thei priest with hym, and they ran after him, &amp; at the laste they ouertoke him, and than the marchant drewe his sworde, &amp; would haue smttē him but the priest would not suffer him, and than made he fast the horse agayn and so droue the iourney to an ende. Whan the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunt was come home, his wyfe asked how he fared and how he lyked his man he aunswered, not of they best. Than he called Howleglas, and he bad hym tary there that night, and in the mornynge, to departe fro thence, for he sayde he was but a begyler, and a decey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer wher so euer he went. Thā sayd Howleglas good maister that shall I do. And than arose Howleglas er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in the mornyng, and as he was vp: the marchaunt sayde. Eate and drynke your belly full, and ridde the house of you, that I fynde you not here whan that I come agayne, for I must to churche, &amp; whan I return if I fynde you here, stand to that, that shalbe fall. And Howleglas helde his peace, and spake neuer a worde. to him, and than the marchaunt wēt to church. Thā he began for to ryd all the houshold stuffe and bare it into the streate, than came worde vnto his maister to the churche, that all his housholde stuffe stode in the, streate. Than came the marchaunt home, &amp; saw that it was Howleglas that had borne out all his stuffe,
<pb facs="tcp:18452:29"/> he asked his man why he did so? and Howleglas sayde I did as you bad me: for ye bad me that I should ryd youre house, and so I haue of all youre stuffe, that ye haue. Than sayde the marchaunt to Howleglas de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte fro hence, and come no more here. I geue they warnyng for here is no body that thankes the for thy labour. And than departed Howleglas his waye: and so was the marchaūt faine to cary in his gere agayne that Howleglas had borne out.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas was desyred to dyner.</head>
               <p>IN Lunē borough dwelled a flute maker that knewe vacabundes by syght. And ō a time it fortuned him to spy Howleglas, to whom he said. To morowe I desyre you to dine with me. Than Howleglas thāked him, &amp; he sayd y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he wold. And than departed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> flutemaker, &amp; on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> morow at none, Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas went to the pype makers house, &amp; whan he was, ther, the dores were shyt. And be taried till none was past, &amp; than he knew wel y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he was greatly deceiued, &amp; so he returned home again. And on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mornynge as he walked in the market, he spied the pipe maker, &amp; than went he to him, &amp; thāked hym for hys byner, &amp; he sayd whā ye byd a bodi to diner, ye shyt all your dores. And the pype maker said. I bad yom come to dyner. Than sayd Howleglas your dores were shit. Than laughed the pype maker &amp; sayd. Go to my house before, and I shal come after to dynner for ye shall fynde both roste and soden. And than departed howleglas to the pype makers house, &amp; there he founde all true as the pype maker had tolde him. And thā said he to the pype ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers wife. that she shold go as fast as she could to her husbande, for he sayde that he had a greate sturgion,
<pb facs="tcp:18452:30"/> geue him and he said that he woulde turn the spit to that she came agayne. The woman sayd good Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas, kepe the house tyll that I come agayne, and let no body in. Than departed the womā with her maid towardes her husbande as fast as she could and met with hym bi the waye. And whan he saw her: he asked her whether she went so fast? And she said to help him For she sayd that Howleglas had told her that ye had a sturgion geueuen you, and he sayd y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ye bad that we shold cōe &amp; helpe you for it was so gret that you were not able to bere it. Than was the mā angry, and sayd Knowe ye not well that Howleglas ys suche a moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and a deceiuer? than went he home with his wife &amp; whan he came home, he knocked at y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> dore, and How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas sayde let be your knockyng, for the hoste hathe charged me, that I should let no gest in tyll dyner bee done. Than went the hoste to his neyghbours and ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryed there tyll Howleglas had dyned, and whan How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas had dyned, than he opened the doore, and than the pypemaker came with all his folke. And whan he was within, he sayd to Howleglas that it was no ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesti for a gest to shyt his hostise out of the dores. And in this maner he serued the hoste, and his hostise.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas wan a pece of clothe of a man of the countrey.</head>
               <p>HOwleglas wold euer fare wel, and make good chere but he woulde not worke. Than on a tīe cāe he to Olsem, to a goodly company of mē of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> coūtrey. And as he walked he espyed one man alone with a grene cloth on hys arme, than ymagyned he in his minde, how that he might get y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> cloth. So he came to him, and he asked him wher he was dwellyng. And
<pb facs="tcp:18452:30"/> than the husband tolde him: and than departed How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas fro him, and continentli he met with a shottish priest. And an other knaue and he sayde to them, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>syre you to helpe me, and I shall geue you for your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and they sayd they wold. Than said Howleglas whan I call you to recorde to know what colour yō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der cloth is: ye shall say blewe. I wil go before, &amp; come after. than went he to the husbandman, and he asked him how he solde his blewe cloth. than sayde the hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band man that it was grene, &amp; not blewe. I holde .xx. gildens against thy cloth, that it is blewe, than saede the husbandmā I holde you. It is done sayde Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas, and the first man that comes hereby, shall be the Iudge thereto. Agreed sayd the husbandman, &amp; than made Howleglas a sygne to the mē, that he had hired and they came. than sayde the husband man, we two striue what colour this cloth as I pray you breke out stryfe. than the felow said it is fayre blew cloth, than said y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> husband mā ye be to false for me to medle with for it is made betwyxt you two to deceyue me. than sayd Howleglas cause that ye saye we be agreed, let hym go here cometh a priest, wil ye be contēted what he sayeth? and the man of the countre sayde yes. thā came the priest by, than sayd Howleglas I praye you to tel vs, what colour this cloth is? the priest sayd ye ie well ynough what nede you to aske me. the husbād man sayd I know the colour of the cloth wel ynough but these two men say it is an other colour and there fore we stryue: than sayde they prieste what haue I to do with our stryuing? than sayde the husbandman I praye you syr departe vs of oure stryuing. than sayde the priest. I can se no other, but that is a fayre blewe.
<pb facs="tcp:18452:31"/> And thā sayd the husbanmā, and ye were not a priest in fayth ye did lye, for ye be thre falsemen. But sythē ye be a priest. I must beleue you. And than gaue he Howleglas thei cloth, and wente his waye. Than did Howleglas with his .ii. felowes clothe them with the husbandmans cloth againste the wynter. But the good poore man prayed to god, many a tyme and ofte that the deuill might take them al thre for the poore man was they worse all they dayes of hys lyfe after that great losse.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas gaue .xx. gyldens to .xii. poore men for christes loue</head>
               <p>ON a time came Howleglas to Hauoner, where he did many vertuous thīges. On a tyme rode Howleglas without the towne, and as he rod he mer with .xii. blinde men to whom he said, whether wil ye go? The blinde men hering that he was on horseback they put of their cappes, for they wende that he had bene a great gentleman, and saide, we haue bene at a doale of a rycheman, that died yesterdai in the town Than sayd Howleglas. I take gret thought for you how you shall do this winter, for me thinke you shall frese to death, before the winter be done. And thā he sayde holde here is .xx gildens and returne agayn all you to the place where that I was lodged, and he na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his host, &amp; he bad them make good chere til win<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter were done. And than they thanked hym, for they thought that he had geuē them moui but he did not And than departed they to the place, whether he sēt them, &amp; the thought y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> some of the company had the mony. And whā y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> they came to the Iune, the said to the hostise y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> by the way as they went, thei met with
<pb facs="tcp:18452:31"/> a good man y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> gaue them .xx. gildens for gods sake, and he bad vs come hither, and make good chere therfore for he said y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he had bene lodged here, &amp; for his sake we shold haue good chere. whan the hoste herde that they had mony, he toke thē in, &amp; made thē good chere. And whan that their .xx. gildens were spent, than said the hoste to them. Nowe will ye reken good brethren, for now the .xx. gildens be spent. The blynd men sayd we be contented to pay you, &amp; than spake on of the blīde men &amp; sayd. He that hath twenty gildēs pay our hoste And than said the one to the other. I haue not the .xx gyldens. Nor I haue not the twenty gyldens. And than some sate and clawed their head, &amp; some clawed their arme. And than they knew that the were decey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued. Than thought the hoste in his mynde what shal I do with them? Shall I let them go that they spend me no more mony? Nay not so. Thā shyt he the blind men in the stable, and brought to them hay &amp; strawe. And whan that Howleglas thought that al the mony was spent: than came he ryding in to the same Inne, where the blynde men were, and he had chaūged hys clothyng that they should not knowe hym, and so en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Inne where the blynd men were and he led his horse into the stable wher the pore men were. And he had set vp his horse: he came to his hoste, and asked his hoste wherfore that he had kept the blynde mē in the stable, so faste shyt in? And he asked hī what harme they had done to hym? Than sayde thei hoste. I woulde that they were together in the water so that I had my costes payde me, and than he tolde hym all the matter. And than sayde Howleglas. And you had a borowe woulde you lette, them goo. And the
<pb facs="tcp:18452:32"/> hoste sayde yes with a good wyll. Than sayde Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas I wyll go see, if I can fynde any borowe for thē. Than went he to the curate of the churche and sayde Maister parsō I haue an hoste, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> this night was takē with the fende I desyre you for to helpe hym. The cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate saide with a good wyl, but you must tary two or thre daies, for it maye not be done in haste: well sayde Howleglas that is well saide but I will go fetche his wife that she may here what you say. And y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> priest said I shall tel to her the same that I told to you without fayle. And than went Howleglas home to his hoste, &amp; he tolde hym that he had founde a borow, and that it was the parsone of the churche, and let your wyfe go with me &amp; she shal here him speke y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same that he hath sayde to me, and than was his hoste glad and he sende his wife with Howleglas, to the curate. And whā the were come to the curate: Howleglas said to him, mai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ster parsone here is the wyfe of the man, that I spake of to you, now tell her the same that you haue said to me. And the curate sayd with a good wil. than said he to they woman, tary a daye or two: and I shall helpe your husbande well. And than was the womā glad, &amp; returned home agayne withe Howleglas, and whan she came home: she told her husband what the curate sayd, wherof the host was glad, and he went vnto the stable and let the blynde men lose and they went ther way. And than Howleglas rekned with his hoste, and so departed from thēce, and whan the thyrd day came than went the woman to the priest, and she asked him twente gildens that the blynde man had spende. The curate asked her, hath your husbande that ye told to me, and the womā said no. Than said the curate, that
<pb facs="tcp:18452:32"/> is the false deuil that wold haue the mony. Thā saide she what false deuill menest thou? Geue me mi moni for my costes: than saide the curate to the woman. It was tolde me that your husbande was taken with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> false deuyll brynge hym hether, and I shall helpe hym therof by the grace of god: than sayd the woman to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> priest suche begylers fynde I many. Now you should pay me for my costes: you bring to me a bacrekening and you say my husband is taken with the deuyll, and that you shall knowe shortly. And than she ran to her husbande and tolde hym how the priest said to her and whan the hoste hard those wordes: he was angry, and toke the spit with the rost that lai at the fyre, and ran to the priestes chambre. And whan they curate spyed hym he was a frayde, &amp; called the neighbours to help him, and he made a signe of the holy crosse before him and he cryed for help to take that mā that was so be set with the deuil, than sayd the hoste, thou priest pay me my mony, and the prieste gaue hym no aunswere. Than would the hoste haue run thorow him with the hote spyt, but the neyghbours went betwene them &amp; departed them, and they helde the hoste stil with gret, payne from maister persone. But as long as the hoste lyued he asked his mony of the priest, for the costes of the blynde men, but the priest aunswered to him that he ought hym nought and nought he would pay him, but sayd and you be take a with a deuyll, I shall helpe you therof. But neuer after loued on the other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas feared his hoste. with a dead woulfe.</head>
               <p>IN y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> setleuen dwelled an Inne holder that was very spyteful &amp; mockyng, and he praysed great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:18452:33"/> his boldnesse. Vpon a tyme it befell in the wenter season, when there had bene a greate snowe. Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas came reding withe other thre marchauntes fro Sasson to ysetleuen, &amp; it was very late or they came there, &amp; whā they were come: the entred into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> Iune that the man kept. Than sayde their hoste angerly wher haue you ben so late, it is no tyme now to take your Iune? Than they aunswered. Be ye not angrie, for we haue bene hounted with a woulfe in the snow we could not scape till nowe. Than the hoste mocked them, because they .iiii. were huntyng of on woulf, &amp; said, if there came .x. woulfes to me in y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> field, I wold haue slayne thē euerichone, &amp; mocked y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> marchaūtes tyl thei went to bed. And howleglas sate bi the fyre, &amp; herde al to gether. Than should they go to bed. And it fortuned that Howleglas &amp; the marchauntes should lye in one chambre. And whan the ware in the chābre together: the toke counsayl to gether how the myght stop their hoste of his mocking. Than sayde Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas our hoste is full of mockyng let me a lone I shall pay hym well ynough, that he shall not mocke vs no more. Than promysed they marchauntes to Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas to pay all his costes, and geue hym more monye for his labour. Than sayd Howleglas do your Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and busynesse of your marchaundyse, and whan ye haue it, come a gayne and lodge at this Inne: &amp; ye shal fynde me here, &amp; than we shal make our host that he shal mocke no more. And thā arose y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> marchauntes in the morning and called the hoste, &amp; payed hym for their costes, and Howleglas also. Than they tooke their horses, &amp; departed from thence. And whan they were paste a lytle, he cryed to they marchauntes take
<pb facs="tcp:18452:33"/> hede that the woulfe byte you not in mockage. The thanked their hoste because he gaue them warning before. And as they rode: Howleglas foūd a woulfe that was frosen to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> deth, and that he toke vp, and put in a bagge, and layd it before hym, and than the retourned agayne to ysetleuen, to that Inne wher the were lodged before. And he kept y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> woulf so close that no man knew therof. And when the nyght was was come &amp; that they sat all at supper: thā the hoste began to laugh at them, &amp; he resoned agaīst ther har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dines, &amp; agaīst the woulfe. Than said the: so it fortu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned at that time▪ you saide y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you wold sle .x. woulfes but first I wold se you kyl one. And than said y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hoste that should I do alone. And thus they iested tyl the went to bedde. And Howleglas helde his peace, tyll that he and the marchaūtes wēt aboue all together in the chambre. And than sayd howleglas to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes frendes. Let me nowe begyn to worke &amp; wake you a lytle whyle. And than went the host &amp; all his folke were a slepe, than wēte he pryuely into the chambre, &amp; he fetched the ded woulf that was styffe frosen &amp; dressed him with stickes &amp; put two chyldren shoene in his mouth, and made him stand as though he had ben a liue. And than left he y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> woulf standing in the hal, and he came againe into the chambre to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> marchauntes, and whan he was aboue, he &amp; y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes called their hoste. And ther host asked thē what they would haue. Than aunswered y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> to him, that they would haue some drynke, for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> had so gret thyrste that the must nedes drynke. Let your mayd or man brynge vs some, and we wyll paye for it to morowe. Than waxed the hoste angrye and sayde.
<pb facs="tcp:18452:34"/> This is the Sassons maner, for to drynke both daye and nyght, And than he called his mayd, and bad her that she should geue the merchauntd drinke. And thā the mayde rose, and as she went to lyght a candel: she saw the woulfe. with: ii. shoene in his mouth. Thā she was afrayd and ran to the gardeyn, for she thought, that he had eaten both the chyldren, than called the a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne. Than called the hoste his mā. and bad hym a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rise and bere the Sassons drynke. Than arose he and lyghted a candle, for he wēd that the mayd had slept stell. Than loked he asyde and sawe the woulfe stande he was a frayd, and he thought that the woulfe had eaten the mayde, and let fal thei candle and rā into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> seller. Than called Howleglas and the marchaūtes the third time, and prayed that he himself wold bring them some drinke for the sayde there came no bodye, or els geue them a candle, and they wold drawe it thē selfe. Than arose the hoste hymselfe, for he wend that his man and his mayde were fallen a slepe agayn, and than lyghted he a candle, and whan that he had done, he loked asyde and spyed the woulfe: and he was so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayde, that he fel vnto the ground, and than arose he and cryed to the marchaūtes, and he prayed them for to come helpe him, for there was a woulf, that had ea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten both his man and his mayde. And this harde thei mayd in the garden, and the man in the seller, &amp; come to help their maister, and the marchauntes also. And Howlealas laughed at this hardy man, that woulde haue slayne ten woulfes, and he was made afraide of one deade woulfe. And whan they hoste sawe y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> it was done in mockage: than was he a shamed, and he wyste not what for to say. And than left he his bostyng, and
<pb facs="tcp:18452:34"/> Iestyng, and went to bed agayne. And on the morow it was knowen through the towne, wherof the hoste was sore ashamed. And than in the mornīg arose the marchauntes and paied ther costes, and Howleglas also, and rode their waye. And than neuer after pray sed the hoste his manhode,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howleglas fleed a hounde: and gaue the skyn for halfe his dyner.</head>
               <p>ON a tyme came Howleglas verye late into an Inne wher the host was not at home, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the hostyse, this hostyse had a bloud hoūde y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which she loued very well and as she had nothyng to do, she toke the hounde on her lappe, and played with him &amp; Howleglas satte by the fyre drinking a potte of bere and the hostyse had taught her hounde to drinke bere in a dyshe, and as Howleglas was drynkynge of hys bere, the hound fauned on him and wagged his tayle on Howleglas, and than sayde thei hostyse, geue they hounde some drynke in his dyshe, for that is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, and Howleglas sayd with a good wyl, and than gaue he the hounde often to drinke, and he gaue him also parte of al thyng that was on the table, that the hounde was as full as he myght be, &amp; than went he &amp; layde hym downe stretchyng hym by the fyre: &amp; withe in a whyle Howleglas had eaten ynoughe, &amp; than as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked thei hostyse yf she would reken and she sayde yes. Than asked he hys hostyse yf she had had a geste, that had eaten her meate, and drinketh her drynke should pay nothing would ye be cōtent therwith. Thā wēt the hostyse, that hed ment him self, and thoughte not of her hounde. Than said she to him good frende, here is no man that eateth here, but he payeth monie or a
<pb facs="tcp:18452:35"/> pledge. Howleglas said I am contēt therwith to pay my parte, and the other must pay his parte. And thā wēt the hostise into her chāber for to do her busines. And thā toke Howleglas the hoūde vnder his gowne and went vnto the stable, &amp; flyed of his skyn. And thā came he agayde to his hostise that sate by y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fyre, &amp; he had the houndes skyn vnder his gowne: and than cal Howleglas for a rekenyng, whan she had rekened: he gaue her half therof. Than asked she him who sholde geue to her that other halfe? Than sayde Howleglas chose you here is my parte, ye had an other geste that went awaye and payde nothyng, and heate &amp; dranke, as well as I dyd, lette hym pay the other halfe of the moni Than sayd the hostise, what gest was that and what pledge had he to geue? Thā sayde Howleglas, the best coate that he had on. Than drew he out the dogges skyn, and sayde to his hostise here is the beste coate that the gest hath. And whan she saw her doggs sckyn: than spake she very angerly, and cursedly wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore haue ye flyed my hounde? Than sayd Howleglas let alone your barning and your cursyng in this ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner for it is your faut, for ye bad to me that I should geue to your hounde meate and drynke and I told to you that the gest had no moni, &amp; ye said that ye would not trust hym, but that ye would haue a pledge or mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney to paye for his costes: so haue I broughte to you the best cote that he hath for a pledge. Than was thei hostise more angry, &amp; sayde: Go out of my house short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and neuer come here more within my dores. Than sayde Howleglas. Shall I go out of your dores: naye but I shall ryde out of your dores. Than toke he his fadell and sadled his horse, &amp; lyght on him And or he de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parted
<pb facs="tcp:18452:35"/> from thence, he sayde to his hostise. Repe well your pledge, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ye may haue your mony. And within a while I shal come vnto you vnbiddē. And if I drinke not of your drinke: than nede I not to paye nothing. And than departed he fro thence, and rode his waye</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas serued the same host<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce an other tyme, and howe he laye. on a whele.</head>
               <p>WIthin a whyle after came Howleglas to Staf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, in the same Inne where he had bene lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged before: and he had done other clothes on, because that his hostyse should not know him. And whan he was come into the Inne, he spyed a whele lye theirby and than he alighted &amp; came &amp; layde hym theron, and bad hys hostyse good morowe. And he asked her, if she harde any newes of howleglas? And she sayde nay, what should I here of him? I can not suffer him to be named. howleglas saide? what harme hath he done to you, that ye may not here speke of him? he is a knaue, in dede, I neuer herde tell yet y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he came in any place, but or he departed he did some shrewde touche. Than said the hostise that is truthe. For it is but .viii. daies agone that (for the great chere that I made to hym) like a treitoure he flayed my hounde, and he gaue me thei skyn for my meate and drynke, Than sayde how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leglas that was a knauy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he touche. And the woman saide therfore shall he come to euill ende. Than saide howleglas Is this all his rewarde? It is not thre houres agone sithen I sawe hym lye vpon a whele. Than said the hostise, if I had knowen that I should haue bette him with a staffe, that I should haue bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken some of his rybbes, for that he hathe done to me.
<pb facs="tcp:18452:36"/> And than arose Howleglas and sayde, let be your an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, for whan I spake to you he laye vpon the whele And nowe adewe I come not here agayne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How Howleglas set his hostyse vpon the hote asshes with her bare arse.</head>
               <p>AS Howleglas was come fro Rome, he came to an Inne where his hoste was not at home And whan he was within, he asked his hostyse if that she knewe not Howleglas, and the hostyse sayde nay: but I here say that he is a false deceyuer and begiler than sayde Howleglas wherfore saye ye so ye knowe him not thā said the hostise that is truth but I haue herd speke much of his vnhappinesse than sayd How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas: good womā he hath done to you neuer no har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, wherfore slaunder ye him for the wordes of other people, the hostyse sayd: I saye no other of hym, than the people do. For I haue hearde him be spoken of, of many of my gestes, that haue lodged bere. Than held Howleglas his peace, &amp; spake no more til in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng, and than spred he abrode the hote asshes on the harthe, and than toke he the hostyse out of her slepe, &amp; set her thereon on her bare arse, &amp; so was hys hostyse well brenned, than sayde he to her. Nowe may ye say boldely, that ye haue sene the false deceuer and begy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Howleglas: than cryed y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> hostyse for help &amp; lowred vpon hym Than went he out of her dores and sayde to her. Should not mē correcte &amp; repreue slaūderers and backbyters, that saye it of men, and neuer sawe them, nor neuer had done harme to them. yes it is a charytable thyng to do. And than tooke he hys horse and departed fro thence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas serued a holāder w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a rosted aple.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18452:36"/>
               <p>VPon a time came Howleglas to And warpe to an Inne, where was many holaders me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. And he brought with hym .ii. egges whiche he ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted for to eat, for he was sycke &amp; coulde eat no fleshe. And this seyng a holander sayde. ye Thomme of the countrey, wyl not your hostyse mete serue you but y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ye must bring meat with you wene ye that ye should haue no meat here: and with those wordes, he toke y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> egges and supped them vp, and whā he hadde done. he gaue too Howleglas the shelles, and sayd to hym: holde here is thei bore, the relykes be gone, and than laughed all the gestes at that touch, and Howleglas also, and in the euenynge fetched Howleglas a fayre apple and cut out all the core therof, and put therī a strong purgacion, and rosted the apple in the fire and than tooke howleglas the apple and cut it in pieces. vpon his trenchour, &amp; strawed therof poudre of gyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and set it vpon the table and wēt from the table as though he would haue gon and fetched more. And as sone as howleglas had tourned his backe, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lander tooke the apple and ate it in a gret haste. And by and by he fell to parbrakyng, and caste vp all that was within hym, and he was very sycke therof, that the hoste and all the gestes wend that he should haue dyed of the apple. And than sayde howleglas to they gestes: be not a frayde of hym for it is a lytle purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, that I haue geuen hym, he was to hasty to eate the apple so sōe, I shold haue warned him therof. For the rosted apple coulde not suffre y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> rere egges in hys mawe, but that they must nedes come out agayn: &amp; than the gestes made good chere and laughed. And whan the purgacion had wrought al that it would &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:18452:37"/> that thei holander was a mended, he sayde to Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas. Roste and eate whatsoeuer ye wyll, for I wyll neuer eate with you more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe Howleglas made a woman that solde ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then pottes, to smyte them all in pieces.</head>
               <p>VPon a tyme toke Howleglas his iourney to Bremen, to the byshop, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> loued him wel. For at al tymes he did some mad touche, wherat he made the byshop to laughe. Than on a tyme as the byshop and Howleglas were a walkynge the byshop desyred of him, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he would do some meri Iest, but Howleglas went talkyng to hym selfe as though he had sayd his pater noster, and answered not the byshop. But at the last he saide to hym, I praye the to se some newes? And he said he wold. But he praied the bishop to tari a whyle. And he gaue him silence. And in the meane whyle went Howleglas to a woman y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hathe earthen pottes to sel ī y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> market, the which pottes he bought on a condicon, that whan he made a signe to her: than she shold smite al y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> pottes in pieces. And she graūted to hym. And than he payed her &amp; returned to the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop. And whan he was come, the byshop asked hym where he had bene? And howleglas sayde I was at church. he said my lord go wyth me vnto the market. And so he did. And whan they were there howleglas said to the byshop Se you the woman with y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> earthē pottes? I shall stande here still by you, &amp; speke neuer a worde: &amp; yet shal I make her to smite her pottes al in pieces. Than said the byshop I holde the .xxx. gildens, that thou shalt not do it. And howleglas dyd holde, the .xxx. gildens with the byshop. And than went they into the towne house, &amp; there they taryed. And than
<pb facs="tcp:18452:37"/> cryede, and called the woman, &amp; at the laste made he the sygne to her that was made betwene them. And than tooke she a staffe, and smyt vpon the pottes so long till that she had broken them eueri chone, so that the byshop and all they that were in the market place did laugh therat. And as the byshop was come home than called he Howleglas a syde vnto him, and sayde. Tell me shortly what thynge ye dyd to the woman, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> ye made her take a staffe, and smyte all thei pottes to peces, and than shal I geue vnto you the .xxx. gildens Than said Howleglas to the byshop. My lorde I dyd it not with sorcery nor witchecraft, but I had payd y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> woman before for her pottes, &amp; we were both agreed And than laughed the byshop therat, and gaue vnto Howleglas .xxx. gildens, and he made hym to swere on a boke, that he should not shewe no body y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> thinge &amp; he sayd he would geue hym a fat oxe. Than sayd How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas, that thing shall I do with a good wyll, &amp; speke neuer a woorde. And than departed Howleglas fro thence, and he let the byshop do what he would. And than went the byshop, that whan he shoulde make a sygne to her, thā should she smyte the earthen pottes all in pieces, and this was the cunnynge that than Howleglas dyd. Than were all thei nobles asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and angry in theire mynde wyth the byshop, but they durst not speake one woorde but clawed theyre heades, whan that they sawe theyr fatte oxen before, their face that they had geuen to the byshop for that foolysh deede. But after they comforted them selfe agayne, and sayde. He is oure Lorde and mayster, and yf that he had asked the oxen for noughte, wee woulde haue geuen them to hym, and Howleglas
<pb facs="tcp:18452:38"/> had for his parte one of thei fat oxen, wherof he was glad as the other did so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the gift amounted to .xx. fat oxen: and than went euery man home, &amp; fetched a fat oxe and broughte it vnto the byshop: and whan that they were all come in, they stode talkyng with the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop and than came Howleglas riding by them, and he sawe all the oxen stande there, thā he sayd vnto the byshop this gaynes is half mine, thā said he to How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leglas, wil you not holde that thing that ye haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised me, and than sayd Howleglas yes, for an other fat oxe. than gaue the byshop vnto Howleglas a fat, oxe and he bad him that he shoulde departe and so he dyd and lefte the byshop with all his lordes talkinge: than called the byshop all the nobles together, &amp; whā that they were come he sayde to them. Nowe shall I shewe vnto you all this greate cunnyng of the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of the pottes openly than saide he to them, this is it. Howleglas had bene before with that woman y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> solde the earthen pottes in the market, &amp; he had payd her for all the pottes, and he bad to her than whan he shold make a signe to her, than shold she smite the ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then pottes all in peces, and thys was the cunnynge that Howleglas did. Than were the nobles ashamed and angry in theyr mynde with the byshop, but they durst not speke one worde, but clawed theire heades, whan the sawe their fat oxen before their face, that they had geuen to the byshop for that folish dede: but after they comforted them selfe agayn and said: he is our lord and maister, and if that he had asked thei oxē for nought, we would haue geuen them to hym. And Howleglas hadde for his parte one of the fat oxen, wherof he was glad.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:18452:38"/>
               <head>¶ How Howleglas brake the stayres that thei mon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes should come down on to mattyns, and howe they fell downe into the yarde.</head>
               <p>HOwleglas as he waxed old and feble: and had bene in many coūtreys: than begā he to take a litle repentaunce on him, and thought to go to be a religious persone. Than toke he his way to Merien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall. And whan he came ther he went into the abbay to the abbot, and whā he came to him, he desired of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> abot that he might be a brooder in the place, and to haue a place, and he promysed the abbot y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> he would leue in the abbay all y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> mony that he had. Than sayd the abbot to him, &amp; iested with him, for he was a me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry iester, that he shold haue a place, but he must haue an office there with for to doo some labour for ye se well, that all my brethren do that thyng that I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde them, and take y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> office that is geuen vnto them, and be cōtent therwith. Thā sayd Howleglas to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> abbot, what soeuer it please you to bid me do, I shall do it with a good wyll. Than said the abbot the labour is not gret that I shall geue vnto you: for ye shall be porter, so that ye may haue cōuersaciō with the people dayly, and no other thing, than for to open the gate, and for to shit it agayne. Than sayd Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas to the abbot. God thanke you my lorde, that ye haue ordeyned for me a poore old man, so light an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and therfore shal I do al that ye bid me, and leue all that ye for byd me. than sayde the abbot to hym. take here is the keyes, ye must not let in euery body, nor scarce let in the .iii. or the .iiii. for ther be so many vacabundes and land rynners. For if that ye should let them all in that comes, the would eat &amp; drinke so
<pb facs="tcp:18452:39"/> much, that at the yeres ende the wold bring y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> place. to a lowe ebbe. Than sayd Howleglas to the abbote That shall I do with a good will. And than kepte he the gate and whan that the seruauntes and munkes should haue comein thā would he let in no more, but the .iii. or the .iiii. And than they complayned to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot of Howleglas, &amp; told hym that Howleglas was a deceuer, and a begyler of folke, for he would not let them in, that belonged vnto the place. Than called y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> abbot Howleglas to him and he asked him why that he dyd not let in the seruauntes of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> place? And How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas aunswered, I haue done as ye bade me, for ye bad me that I should let in but the third or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> fourth and no more, and so I dyd, and therefore haue I not brokē your commaundement. Than said the abbot ye haue dōe lyke a false knaue, &amp; therfore shall I put y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> out of thy office, for ye wil not leue your false tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. And than gaue he that office to an other mūke. And than said he to howleglas, this shall be your of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, you shal tel euery night how many mūkes come to matyns, and ye mysse one: ye shall out of y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> abbay. Than sayd Howleglas to the abbot. My lord y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> were I loth for to do, for to go out of the a bay, well I will do after youre commaūdement, but the abbot gaue to hym that offyce, because that he shold haue hī out of the abbay, and so for to be ryd of hym. And Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas thought in his mynde, not for to tary long. And than went Howleglas &amp; pulled awaye .ii. or .iii. stepes of the stayres, that the mūkes should come down on to matyns. And at mydnyght came the pryour fyrste that was a good olde man, and was wonte to be they fyrst. And whan he thought to haue gone down: he fel
<pb facs="tcp:18452:39"/> and brake his leg. And thā he cryed pyteously, so that the other munkes herd him, and came running haste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye for to see what that he ayled and lacked &amp; than fel they eche after other downe the stayres. Than in thei mornyng complayned the munkes to the abbot, and shewed hym howe that Howleglas had serued them. Than was the abbot more angri, and said to Howle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glas, what haue ye done? Howleglas sayd as ye bad me, for ye bad me y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> I should tel y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> munkes whan they came to matins, and so I haue done, looke here is the tayle. Than said the abbot go out of the abbai for ye haue told them like a false knaue. And than departed Howleglas fro that abbay and went to Mollen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas bought creame of the womon of the coūtrey, that brought it for to sel to Maryandra.</head>
               <p>WIthin a whyle after or y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> he would enter into y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> abbay of Mariandra to be a munke, he went a walkyng on the market daye to Bremen, wher he sawe many women standing there to sell creame. And than went Howleglas to the house where he was lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and borowed a tub of his hostise, and went again in to y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> market. And whan he was there: he set downe his tub and came to a woman of the countrei and he asked they pryce of her creame. And whan they ware both a greed: he made her for to put y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> creme into his tub and than wēt he to an other, and agreed with her also &amp; made her to put her creme into his tub, and so went he fro the on to the other, tyll that he had made all the women that had ther creme: to put it into his tub. And whan he had soo done: than asked thei poore women theire money of Howleglas, for they woulde departe home. Than sayde Howleglas to the women
<pb facs="tcp:18452:40"/> ye must do so much for me, as to trust me these eight dayes. for I haue no mony at this tyme. Thā ware the women of the countrey angry, &amp; the ran to they tub for to take euery one of them their cream again for the would not trust him. And as thei wold haue taken their creme agayn, than began they to fal to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the eares, &amp; sayde. Thou takest more than thou should haue. And the other stode all wepyng, &amp; sayde to them. Shall I loose my creame? And other twayn were tumbling by the here, in the myddes of the canel. And thus the pulied and haled on y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> other that at the last the tub fel downe, &amp; arayed thē very foule, so that they were all dysfygured &amp; wist not of whome the should be auenged of. And thā arose the and asked where is this false knaue, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> hath bought our mylke, and hath dysceued vs so, for had we hym here amonge vs, we shoulde christen hym here in the creame, that is in the cannell, &amp; paint him therwith as wel as we be, for he is a false begyler and dyscey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. But he was gone fro thence for he cast before y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> such a thyng should folowe. And whan the burgeys of the town and many other folke of the town sawe that the cannels ran with creame. Than went thei to the market place for to se. And whā y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ware ther: they asked how the creme was spylt, and thā it was tolde them. And whan that the knew it than the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home laughyng, and praysed greatli y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and suttelte of Howleglas.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas came to a scoler to make verses with hym to that vse of reason. And howe that Howleglas began as after shall folowe.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:18452:40"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>¶ Howleglas.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ars with septer, a king coronate</l>
                     <l>Furius in affliction, and taketh no regarde</l>
                     <l>By terrible fightyng, he is our prymate</l>
                     <l>And god of battell, and person ryght froward.</l>
                     <l>Of warries the tutor, the locke, and the warde</l>
                     <l>His power his might, who can them resyst</l>
                     <l>Not all this worlde, if that him selfe lyst,</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The scholer.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>¶ Not all this worlde, who tolde the so?</l>
                     <l>Where is that written, ryght fayne wold I see?</l>
                     <l>ye came lyke a foole, and so shall ye go.</l>
                     <l>By one person only, deceiued ye may be</l>
                     <l>And by astronomy, I tell it vnto the</l>
                     <l>If that wyll not helpe, some shyft shall I fynde</l>
                     <l>By craft, or cunnyng, Mars for to blynde.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Howleglas.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>¶ Venus a god of loue most decorate</l>
                     <l>The floure of women, and lady most pure</l>
                     <l>Louers to concorde, she doth aye aggregate</l>
                     <l>with parfyte loue, as marble to oure</l>
                     <l>The knot of loue, she knittes on them sure</l>
                     <l>With frendly amite, and neuer to discorde</l>
                     <l>By dedes, thought, cogitacion, nor worde.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The scholer.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>¶ Not to discorde, yet dyd I neuer see</l>
                     <l>Knowe, nor here tell, of louers suche twayne</l>
                     <l>But some faute there was, learne this of me</l>
                     <l>Other in thought, or yet in wordes playne</l>
                     <l>your reasons be nought, your tong goeth in vayne</l>
                     <l>By naturall person: suche loue is not found</l>
                     <l>In Fraunce, Flaunders, nor yet in Englysh ground</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:18452:41"/>
                     <l>¶ The god of wyne, that bachus hath to name</l>
                     <l>The sender of fruytes, that maketh wynes all</l>
                     <l>May slake, or make, or put them in frame.</l>
                     <l>All at his pleasure, and vse dyuryall</l>
                     <l>He may the exalte in lykewyse to fall</l>
                     <l>Their lorde, and maister and chiefe gouernour</l>
                     <l>He may them destroye, and make in a houre.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>The scoler.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l>¶ All to destroy, it is not by his myght</l>
                     <l>Nor yet for to make of that be thou sure</l>
                     <l>(Omnia per ipsum (saint Iohan sayes full ryght</l>
                     <l>Than we call Christ, our god and our treasure</l>
                     <l>Presume not so hye, you fayle of your measure</l>
                     <l>Rede, heare, and see, and bere well a waye</l>
                     <l>Vnknowen vnsayde and for grace thou pray.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <closer>Vale.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head> ¶ Howe Howleglas at Mollem was sycke, &amp; howe he did shyte in the poticaries boxes, and how he was borne in the holy ghoste.</head>
               <p>AS Howleglas was come from Meriendasse. than he fell sycke and whan he was sycke, he went to Mollem, where he was lodged in a poticary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es house, for to make medicines therfore. Than shold the poticarie geue to him a medicine for his sicknesse and than he gaue to wowleglas a stronge purgacion. And in the mornynge the purgacion begon to worke. And than arose Howleglas for to haue gone to they draughte, but he coulde not fynde none: and so he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shyt all thei chambre. And than he toke the .xii. boxes, that the medicins were in, and he shyt in euery one of them, and he said. Here come out the medicines again
<pb facs="tcp:18452:41"/> it were great pity to lose them, for I haue no mony to geue hym for them. whan they potycary hearde these wordes, than was he angry, &amp; he would haue hym no, longer in his house but toke &amp; bare him into an hospi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tal of the holy gost. And whan he was the within, thā he said I haue praied god lōg that the holy gost might cōe vnto me, but my praier is clene cōtrary, for I am come into the holy gost, &amp; he abydeth without me, &amp; I in hym. Than laughed the peple &amp; said. As mē liue: so is their ende. Than herde his mother say that he was sick: than she came to him, and she had thought for to haue had some mony of him, for she was olde &amp; pore, and whan she sawe him, she wepte &amp; sayd. where be ye so sycke. And Howleglas sayd. here betwene the bed &amp; the wal. Than said his mother speke to me one swet word. than said Howleglas to his mother, hony hony, is not y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a swete worde, than saide his mother, tell me some thinge y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> may do me ease, than sayde Howleglas to his mother, whā that you fist: turn your arse with the wynd &amp; than you shal fele no stinke. Than said his mother, geue me some of your good, than said Howle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glas to his mother, he that hath none shall geue none For my good is so secrete that no man can fynde it, &amp; you can finde any take it. And thā Howleglas waxed sicker &amp; sicker, so y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the folke axed him whether that he would be shryuen, for they sawe wel that he shold not recouer. than sayde an olde syster that was a good frende of his she counsailed him to be cōfessed &amp; take repentaunce for his synnes, and so to holy seruant of god. And Howleglas sayd. I wil not cōfesse mē secret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li, for al that I haue done, I haue done it opēly to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men in dyuers landes. and that is wel knowē. For
<pb facs="tcp:18452:42"/> they that I haue done good to, they wil saye good o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> me. And they that I haue done harme to, the wil say harme of me. But I am very sory of two thinges y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> which I could neuer bring to passe in my lyfe. Than sayd the syster be sory of thi sinnes, and be glad that you did not those two thinges, if y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the wer yll. And if the were good, be sory because the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not done. Than sayd Howleglas, it is as me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> take it. For I was sory in my mynd whan I sawe a man pycke his tethe with his knyfe, that I had not s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tten on the end of it. The other is that I am sory for, that I did not driue a woden wedge in all womēs arses, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> were aboue .l. yere, for they be nother clenly nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytable. I desyre it for no othere cause but this y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> is that the should not shyte on the ground, the whiche bringeth fruytes. Than said the sister to Howleglas god saue all womē of that age &amp; all those that bene more. For I here well and you were strong, and that you had your might as you haue had before this tīe you would or you departed wedge mine arse, with a woden wedge, for I am a woman of .lx. yere &amp; more. Than he answered to the sister. I am ryght for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. &amp; heuy because it is not done. Thā aūswered the sister it were much better that the deuil had the. Thā an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>swered Howleglas that is truthe, for a womā is no soner angry but she is worse than the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il. And thā the syster departed and let hym lye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Howleglas deceyued his gostly father.</head>
               <p>ANd as Howleglas was thus sicke, and than they brought to hym a prieste: And whan y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> priest was come there, he thought in his mynd, this
<pb facs="tcp:18452:42"/> hath bene a great<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wherewith he hath g<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the priest vnto him and<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> your selfe, for ye haue done ma<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> must you remebre that you haue<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> how you haue gotten much mony b<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> hode &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bestowe that moni to the w<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and poore p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>stes as I am, and that I counce<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> for to do, and I shall order it well and remembre you here<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ter, and do many masses for you. Than sayde Howleglas. Good father if it please you to come at noone agayne, than shal I make redy some mony for you: Than was the priest glad, &amp; than departed. Thā tooke Howleglas an earthen pot ād fylled it half ful of turdes, &amp; he strawed theron a lytle mony, soo that the durte was couered. And whan it was noone, the priest came and he sayd to Howleglas. Frend shall I haue that y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you promised me? And Howleglas sayde ye. Than he set the pot before hym, and sayde. Take now your selfe. but be not to hasty, nor put not your hand to depe. Than sayde the priest I shall do as you byd me. And Howleglas dyd open the pot, and he bad the priest to grype softlye, for it was almost ful. Thā was the priest hasty, and put his hand into the pot, &amp; he gryped a great handfull. And when he felt it softe: he pulled out his hande, and it was all to be shitten. Thā the priest sayde, ye maye well be called a decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer &amp; begyler, that haue deceiued his ghostly father, and whan ye be at the poynte of death. Than sayde Howleglas to the priest. Good syr dyd I not shewe vnto you before y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> you shold not grype to depe? And if that ye were couetous, it was not my faut. Thā
<pb facs="tcp:18452:43"/> sayd the <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ctousnesse all other, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> it was great pyty that y<seg rend="sup">u</seg>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>yng, whan thou sholdest haue bene <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eke, and than the priest departed frō <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Howleglss called y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> priest agayne, and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#uom" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to hym. Maister parson come agayne, &amp; take your money with you. But he went his waye and made it as he harde it not.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Holeglas made his testament.</head>
               <p>IN the meane time wexed Howleglas sycker &amp; sicker, Than he called for y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> lordes to make his tastamente. And whan they were come: he gaue hys goodes in .iii. partes. One parte to his kynsfolke, an other to the lordes of Molē, and the other to the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>son of Molen, whā soeuer he died. And he asked to be buryed in christen mans buriall, and to syng for hys soule, Placebo and Dixig, with masses &amp; other good seruyces, after the custome and vsans. And than he shewed to them a great chest y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> was wel barred with yron, and fowre keyes therto belongyng, and he told vnto them, that in that chest was all his good, &amp; than he gaue the cheste to them to kepe, that wer right he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uy for him. And thā within a moneth after his death than the foure should take the keyes therof, and opē the cheste, and deale all the money for his soule. And within a whyle after he departed. And whan he was dead: they wound hym in a wynding shete, and after in a coffyn, and after on a bere. Than came the prye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stes and feched hym to church and song for hym pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cebo and dyrīg. And in the meane time came in a sow with her pygges, and went vnder y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> bere, for she had
<pb facs="tcp:18452:43"/> found the taste of dead flesshe &amp; with her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#uom" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he can down the bere, wherof the priestes and clerkes wer a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>frayde, and they sawe that it was downe, than they ran so fast y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> eche fell in others necke, for the thought that he had bene rysen agayne and so they lefte hym there. And than the systers of a nonnery tooke the corse, and brought it to graue and buried it. And whā a moneth was past: than came the thre parties for to vnlocke the cheste, and for to deale the money for his soule. And whan that they had opened the cheste: the founde no other but stones therin. Than the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered therof, and the one lokēd on the other, and they parson had wende, that the lordes had had the money because they had the chest in kepinge. And the lordes wende that his frendes had opened the cheste and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kē out the tresure, &amp; put in stones the whyle that he was sycke. and so to haue shyt the cheste agayne. And his frendes wende that the curate had cōueied y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> tre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>sure whan that he confessed hym. And than in a gret anger they departed fro thēce for at the last y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> knew that it was he that had dō it for to mocke them. And after that the lordes and the curate agreed together agayne, and so to bury hī vnder the galowes. And so they dyd. And as they were deluīge of his graue, he stanke so sore, that thei could not abide y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> ayre therof And so the couered hym wyth earth agayne and lete hym lye styll, and so they departed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How Holiglas was buryed.</head>
               <p>THus as Howleglas was deade, than they brought hym to be buryed. And as they would
<pb facs="tcp:18452:44"/> haue put the coffyn into the pytte wyth .ii. cordes, the corde at the fete brake, so that the fote of the coffī fel into the botome of the pyt, and the coffyn stode bolt vpryght in the myddes of the graue. Than desyred y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> people that stode about the graue that tyme, to let y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> coffyn to stande bolte vpryght. For in his lyfe tyme he was a very maruelous man, and he did many wō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull thynges, and shall be buryed as meruesousli and in this maner they left Howleglas stand bolt vp ryght in his graue, and they couered him with earth And than they layde a stone. And on the stone was grauen an oule holding a glasse with her clawes And theron was grauen this scripture. <q>
                     <p>Presume no man a waye this stone to take. For vnder this stone was Howleglas bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried late.</p>
                     <p>In the yeare of our Lorde God. M.CCC. &amp; fyftie.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:18452:44"/>
            <head>¶ Here begynneth the table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>HOwe Howleglas as he was borne was christe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned .iii. tymes vpon one daye.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas aunswered a man that asked the hyghe waye.</item>
               <item>How that Howleglas sat vpon his fathers horse, behynde hym.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas fell fro the rope into the water.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas mother learned hym, ād bad him go to a craft.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas gat bread for his mother.</item>
               <item>Howe Holeglas was stolen out of a bye hyue, by nyght.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas was hyred of a pryest.</item>
               <item>How Holeglas was made a paryshe clarke.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas wold flye fro a house top.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas made hymselfe a physicion, and how he begyled a doctour with hys medicines.</item>
               <item>How Holeglas made a sicke chylde shylde shyte, y<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a fore myght not shyte, and howe he gat great worship therof.</item>
               <item>How Holeglas made hole all the sycke folke that were in the hospytall, where the spere of our lord is.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas was hyred to be a bakers seruāt</item>
               <item>How Howleglas was put in wages, with the fos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Anhalte for to watche vpon a tower, to se whā his enemies came, and than for to blowe an horne to warne them therof.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas wan a great deale of mony wyth a poynt of foolyshnesse.</item>
               <item>How the duke of Lunenborough banyshed How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leglas
<pb facs="tcp:18452:45"/> out of his lande.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas set his hostyse vpon the hoote asshes with, her bare arce.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas toke vpon him to be a paynter.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas had a great disputacion with all the douctours of Pragem in Bemen.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas became a pardoner.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas did eate for money, in the towne. Banberbetche.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas wēt to Rome to speke w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> the pope.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas deceiued .iii. Iewes with durt.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas had gotten the persons horse by his confession.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas was hyred of a blacke smyth.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas was hyred of a shoemaker.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas serued a tayler.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas solde turdes for fat.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas through his subtle disceytes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued a wyne drawer in Lubeke.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas became a maker of Spectacles and howe he could fynde no worke in no lande.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas was hyred of a marchaunt man to be his cooke.</item>
               <item>How howleglas was desyred to dyner.</item>
               <item>How howleglas wane a piece of cloth, of a man of the country.</item>
               <item>How howleglas gaue .xx. gyldens to .xii. poore mē for Christes loue.</item>
               <item>How howleglas feared his host w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a dead woulfe.</item>
               <item>how howleglace flied a hound and gaue the skyn for halfe his dynner.</item>
               <item>how howleglas serued y<seg rend="sup">e</seg> same hostise another tim
<pb facs="tcp:18452:45"/> and laye on a whele.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas serued a holāder w<seg rend="sup">t</seg> a rosted aple.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas made a woman that sold erthen potts to smyte them all in pieces,</item>
               <item>How Howleglas brake the stayres that the mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes should come downe on to matyns, and how thei fell downe into the yarde.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas bought creame of the women of the cuntrey that brought it for to sell.</item>
               <item>How Howlegls came to a scholer, to make verses with him to the vse of reason.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas was secke at Molen and how he dyd shyte in the poticaries boxes, and was borne in the holy ghoste.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas deceiued his ghostly father.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas made his testament.</item>
               <item>How Howleglas was buried.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the lyfe of Howleglas.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprynted at London in Tamestrete at the Vintre on the thre Craned wharfe by Wyllyam Copland.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>